<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The most pleasant and delightful historie of Curan, a prince of Danske, and the fayre Princesse Argentile, daughter and heyre to Adelbright, sometime King of Northumberland Shewing his first loue vnto her, his succeslesse suite, and the low deiections he vnderwent for her sake. His second loue to the same lady vnknowne, taking her for a poore countrie damsell. She (by reason of the vnkindnesse of King Edell her vnckle and gardian) hauing forsooke the court, and vndertooke the profession of a neatheardes mayde. His constant loue (after her long continued vnkindnes) rewarded with her wished consent, their happie nuptials, and mutuall reioycings, his valour and victorious warre with King Edell: and lastly, his peacefull installment in the kingly throne. Enterlacte with many pritty and pithie prayses of beauty, and other amorous discourses, pleasing, smooth and delightfull. By William Webster.</title>
            <author>Webster, William, treatise writer.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1617</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 106 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14878</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25180</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111643</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846930</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846930</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11927</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14878)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11927)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1015:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The most pleasant and delightful historie of Curan, a prince of Danske, and the fayre Princesse Argentile, daughter and heyre to Adelbright, sometime King of Northumberland Shewing his first loue vnto her, his succeslesse suite, and the low deiections he vnderwent for her sake. His second loue to the same lady vnknowne, taking her for a poore countrie damsell. She (by reason of the vnkindnesse of King Edell her vnckle and gardian) hauing forsooke the court, and vndertooke the profession of a neatheardes mayde. His constant loue (after her long continued vnkindnes) rewarded with her wished consent, their happie nuptials, and mutuall reioycings, his valour and victorious warre with King Edell: and lastly, his peacefull installment in the kingly throne. Enterlacte with many pritty and pithie prayses of beauty, and other amorous discourses, pleasing, smooth and delightfull. By William Webster.</title>
                  <author>Webster, William, treatise writer.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[64] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Barnard Alsop for Richard Higgenbotham, and are to be solde at his shop at the signe of the Cardinals Hatte neere S. Sepulchres Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1617.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First word of title is xylographic.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H⁴.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The pleasant history of Curan and Argentile.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of a photostat of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11927:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11927:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE</hi> MOST PLEASANT <hi>AND DELIGHTFVL HISTORIE of Curan, a Prince of Danske, and the fayre</hi> Princeſſe Argentile, Daughter and Heyre <hi>to Adelbright, ſometime King of</hi> Northumberland.</p>
            <p>SHEWING <hi>His firſt Loue vnto her, his ſucceſleſſe ſuite, and</hi> the low deiections he vnderwent for her ſake. His ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond loue to the ſame Lady vnknowne, taking her for <hi>a poore Countrie damſell. She by reaſon of the vnkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> of King Edell her vnckle and Gardian) hauing forſooke the Court, and vndertooke the <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion of a Neatheardes Mayde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His conſtant loue (after her long continued vnkindnes) <hi>rewarded with her wiſhed conſent, their happie</hi> Nup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials, and mutuall reioycings, his valour and victorious warre with King Edell: And <hi>laſtly, his peacefull inſtallment in the Kingly Throne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>ENTERLACTE With many pritty and pithie prayſes of beauty, and other</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous diſcourſes, pleaſing, ſmooth and delightfull.</p>
            <p>By WILLIAM WEBSTER.</p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>Barnard Alſop</hi> for <hi>Richard Higgenbotham,</hi> and are to be ſolde at his ſhop at the ſigne of the Cardinals Hatte neere S. Sepulchres Church. 1617.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:11927:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11927:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE <hi>WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVL M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. THOMAS EVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rard of Heather, in the Countie of Leyceſter, <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
               </hi> all increaſe of ſuch Bleſſings as make this <hi>life happie and comfortable, and of ſuch</hi> Graces, as may make the next Bleſſed and Glorious.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>YR,</hi> purpoſing to impoſe ſome taske on my wandring thoughts ſo to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe their ſomewhat vncomfortable ſtrayings, my raſher election ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly ſingled out this ſubiect, which though ſuting too neerely with my braine in barrennes, the product is this Pamphlet, which peruſed by ſome friends of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, was pronounced worthy the Preſſe. Wherevn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to I the rather referr'd it, that dedicating the ſame vnto you, I might (at leaſt) manifeſt my remembrance of that loue, kindneſſe, and courteſie, which (while my reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence was in loued <hi>Leyceſter-ſhire,</hi>) made mee ſo much affect that Familiaritie, which you then pleaſed to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foord me, in regard wherof my loue leades me to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent this to your patronage, and your affection to Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, makes mee preſume of your acceptance: the grace you giue a Verſe in reading it, makes it pleaſing, if it be
<pb facs="tcp:11927:3"/>but paſſable, therefore I doubt not your liking. And if this (which is not vnlike) gaine your approbation, I ſhall not paſſe for the Cenſures of ſuch as are more apt to finde fault, then able to finde a faulte. Had I but the name of a Poet, and opinion on my ſide, I ſhould relye therevpon as <hi>Caeſar</hi> on his Fortune, yet doth not my obſcuritie diſcourage mee, but rather the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, for Fame is rather to be ventred for then ventred.</p>
            <p>An inſtigation to the writing hereof, was the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation which I heard a Iudicious diuine giue of a yong Student in diuinity, for his dexteritie in Engliſh Poeſie, who affirming it to be an ornament to any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, I was thereby induced to reduce that affection I bore it, to practiſe. And in publiſhing the ſame I haue imitated <hi>Apelles,</hi> who hauing drawne a picture plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to himſelfe, hang'd it in open viewe, that he might heare the verdite of others. Nor is it vnlike but I alſo ſhall haue a ſhoo-maker Cenſuring the Legge, when his skill extends but to the latcher. So (referring it to your fauourable ſuruey, and kinde acceptance) I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly deſire Almightie God to Crowne you, and your adopted-ſelfe, with his beſt bleſſings in this life, and with Immortall glory in the next.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips Kinſman, to be commanded, in a more acceptable ſeruice. <hi>WILLIAM WEBSTER.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:11927:3"/>
            <head>The Author to his Patron.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>T To wiſh your hapineſſe, if that could giue</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>H Happineſſe vnto you, I'de make you bleſt</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O On Earth, ſo long as you on Earth ſhall liue,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>M May you bee euen of Earths beſt things poſſeſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A And may you ioyes enioy when this life's ended,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>S Such as can but by Saintes be apprehended.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>E Euer may you, and your Poſteritee,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>V Vntill diſſolu de ſhall be this mortall frame:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>E Euen till this world ſhall ceaſe a world to bee,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>R Retaine the luſtre of this ancient Name.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A And be chiefe Pillors to ſupport the ſame,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>R Repaire and grace that Houſe, from whence to mee</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>D Deriued is (in part) my Pedegree.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>To <hi>M. Iohn Euerard</hi> Senior, <hi>Gentleman.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>YOu ſole ſuruiuer, yet the eldeſt brother</l>
               <l>Of fower, and of a Siſter, my late Mother;</l>
               <l>Who, (next before you) tendred <hi>Natures</hi> debt,</l>
               <l>Which yet you owe, and long may owe it yet.</l>
               <l>What iſt? your Courage keepes you ſtill aliue,</l>
               <l>To be the firſt, and yet the laſt of fiue.</l>
               <l>Sure t'is your valour; <hi>Deaths</hi> approach thus ſtayes,</l>
               <l>Which was admir'd in your more youthfull dayes.</l>
               <l>If in a mortals lookes may boldneſſe lye</l>
               <l>Which may the pale Horſe-ryder terrifie,</l>
               <l>Then (it may be) he ſhunnes becauſe he feares you,</l>
               <l>And vntill Age ſubdue you, thus forbeares you.</l>
               <l>Your oft-tryde valour, valour oft did trye,</l>
               <l>Which now intombed in your Age doth lye.</l>
               <l>And if your grauitie thinke not vnſit,</l>
               <l>Let theſe lines be the Epitah for it,</l>
               <l>As for your Vertues, they yet liue, and they</l>
               <l>Shall be remembred in your Epitah.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:11927:4"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>READER, Let not thy gentle eye diſdaine</l>
               <l>To walke along my lines ſo ſmooth ſo plaine;</l>
               <l>Delightfull walkes they happily may proue,</l>
               <l>So they may catch thy liking, I thy loue;</l>
               <l>This volume, (though not large) at large diſcouers</l>
               <l>The fortunes of a payre of princely Louers,</l>
               <l>Prince <hi>Curan</hi> and the Princeſſe <hi>Argentile.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He ſtranger, ſhe a natiue of our Iſle.</l>
               <l>He one for lineaments, and gifts of mind:</l>
               <l>Such as the like to him was hard to find:</l>
               <l>And ſure, if to be amorous be no blot</l>
               <l>To vertue, then his vertues had no ſpot,</l>
               <l>And ſhee, a dame whoſe beauty ſo excell'd,</l>
               <l>That in thoſe dayes ſhee was not paralell'd,</l>
               <l>And, if ſhe were not coy more then ſhee ſhould,</l>
               <l>No imputation could on her take hold,</l>
               <l>How loue, from Lordlineſſe doth him debace,</l>
               <l>And makes him to ſupply a peaſants place:</l>
               <l>And how his loue to ſhunne, th'aſſaults of loue,</l>
               <l>From Court to Cottage doth her ſelfe remoue.</l>
               <l>Theſe things are here diſcourſt, and here is ſhowne</l>
               <l>How he the ſecond time loues her vnknowne,</l>
               <l>How long he wooes her, how at laſt he ſped,</l>
               <l>Though not till then, when all his hopes were dead,</l>
               <l>Then how he conquered him in bloudie fight</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:4"/>
               <l>That wrongfully vſurpt his Ladyes right,</l>
               <l>(Then which) his former taske was farre more hard,</l>
               <l>This laſt was eaſie with the firſt compar'd,</l>
               <l>T'was more to him his Ladyes loue to gaine</l>
               <l>Then to giue end vnto a tyrants raigne:</l>
               <l>To conquer her affections was a thing</l>
               <l>More hard to him then to vncrowne a King,</l>
               <l>Nay, all the weapons in theſe wars imployde,</l>
               <l>Againſt the Prince, not him ſo much annoy'd,</l>
               <l>As did his Ladies angry frownes, for thoſe</l>
               <l>Could daunt him more then all his armed foes:</l>
               <l>How he was rayſ'd vnto a Kingly throne,</l>
               <l>That low deiections long had vndergone,</l>
               <l>Concludes this booke, which read vnto the end,</l>
               <l>Perhaps to thee, it may it ſelfe commend:</l>
               <l>Thus (of thy wiſhes) wiſhing thee poſſeſt,</l>
               <l>(For kind acceptance onely.) Thine I reſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:11927:5"/>
            <head>TO THE FAIRE READER, OF THE FAYRER SEX.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>YOu louely <hi>DAME,</hi> whoſe beautie is as much</l>
               <l>As was this louely Dames, faire <hi>Argentile:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For in the world, where ſhould wee looke for ſuch,</l>
               <l>If not where ſhee was bred, in this faire Ile.</l>
               <l>For breeeding ſuch, our Clime; then other Climes</l>
               <l>More fertile is, our times, then former times.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You are the very ſame, yea, you are ſhee,</l>
               <l>Whoſe Beautie in this Booke is ſo commended:</l>
               <l>And though your Name not <hi>Argentile</hi> it be,</l>
               <l>Yet know your ſelfe is ſhee that's here intended.</l>
               <l>Theſe lines were writ for you, of them make vſe,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Beauties</hi> praiſes to your ſelfe reduce.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You liuing, louely <hi>Dame,</hi> t'was for your ſake,</l>
               <l>That this inſuing taske I vndertooke:</l>
               <l>Not hers, ſhee'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dead, ſhee'l no requitall make,</l>
               <l>But at your hands (at leaſt) for thankes I looke.</l>
               <l>To grace what graceth you, I here haue ſought,</l>
               <l>Then deigne to grace me with a gracious thought.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You are faire (as was ſhee) but be not tho,</l>
               <l>Coy (as was ſhee) O varry you in this:</l>
               <l>I would not for the world you ſhould be ſo,</l>
               <l>For then as good that you the world did miſſe.</l>
               <l>Vnleſſe your kindneſſe ſhould (as hers) at laſt,</l>
               <l>Make large amends, for your vnkindneſſe paſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Had I prayſ'd Bountie(ſo)perhaps my paine,</l>
               <l>Might haue bene recompenced with reward:</l>
               <l>Then let me not praiſe Beauty (thus) in vaine,</l>
               <l>Afford me in requitall ſome regard.</l>
               <l>You I haue ſought to pleaſe, and I from you,</l>
               <l>Due thankes, and due reſpect, expect: Adue.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:11927:5"/>
            <head>THE PLEASANT AND delightfull Storie of Prince <hi>Curan,</hi> and <hi>the Princeſſe</hi> Argentile.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THen when our Engliſh Ile (which now in one</l>
               <l>Vnited is, the more our happineſſe)</l>
               <l>Vnder diuided Soueraignety did grone,</l>
               <l>Ichouah ſhield it from the like diſtreſſe;</l>
               <l>Seuen Kings then raigned in this land, but now</l>
               <l>All hearts, all knees, loue one, to one doe bow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>(Then <hi>Diria</hi>) called now <hi>Northumberland,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Was of the foreſaid ſeuen ſmall Kingdomes one,</l>
               <l>Nor was that Scepter ſway'd by one mans hand,</l>
               <l>Diuiſion had the Clime ſo ouergone,</l>
               <l>Two, each a ſemi-king raign'd ioyntly there</l>
               <l>In friendly peace, for they neere Kinſmen were.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Edell</hi> and <hi>Adelbright</hi> the Kings were cal'd,</l>
               <l>For each of them the kingly title beares,</l>
               <l>And each is in the kingly throne inſtal'd,</l>
               <l>Thing ſeldome ſeene) well, after diuers yeares,</l>
               <l>King <hi>Adelbright</hi> deceaſt, and left his Heire</l>
               <l>To <hi>Edell's</hi> ward, young <hi>Argentile</hi> the fayre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:6"/>
               <l>Yet ere he dyes, to <hi>Edell</hi> thus he ſpake,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Edell,</hi> quoth he, my death approacheth neere,</l>
               <l>My Kingly right to thee I doe betake,</l>
               <l>During the nonage of my daughter deare,</l>
               <l>But after it ſhall be to her reſign'd,</l>
               <l>So thou thy ſelfe to mee by oath ſhalt binde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>His oath for this, his promiſe tooke beſide,</l>
               <l>To deale with her, as if his childe ſhee were.</l>
               <l>The good King <hi>Adelbright</hi> ſoone after dyde,</l>
               <l>For whom young <hi>Argentile</hi> ſhed many a teare:</l>
               <l>And time increaſt her griefe, for afterwards</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Edell</hi> nor oath, nor honeſty regardes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Scepter whole now his, hee'l not deuide,</l>
               <l>Vſurping that, that is the Ladies right;</l>
               <l>(Though he from that by oath himſelfe had tide;)</l>
               <l>For in ſole ſoueraignty he found delight,</l>
               <l>By her he knowes he cannot be conſtrain'd,</l>
               <l>Therefore hee'l not forgoe what he hath gain'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Meane while the Lady in deſpight of woes,</l>
               <l>Which ſtill too much afflict her tender heart,</l>
               <l>The fayreſt vnderneath the skie ſhe growes,</l>
               <l>Beauty is hers in full, and not in part;</l>
               <l>Beſides, ſhee's modeſt, ſober, gentle, chaſt,</l>
               <l>Her beautie theſe, and theſe her beauty grac't.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But when her beauty grew yet more mature,</l>
               <l>All beauties then in her ſeem'd to combine,</l>
               <l>Her beautie other beauties did obſcure,</l>
               <l>As ſtarres eclipſed are by <hi>Luna's</hi> ſhine.</l>
               <l>In all the land was none ſo fayre as ſhee,</l>
               <l>In all the world a fayrer could not be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:6"/>
               <l>Her beautie ſeemeth to be be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſoule,</l>
               <l>It doth in excellence ſo much exceede,</l>
               <l>Her eye ſo ſwayes, ſo rules, doth ſo controule,</l>
               <l>And hend the hearts of men, as wind the reede,</l>
               <l>All like, all prayſe, and many loue, but few</l>
               <l>(Diſpayring of their worth) for loue dare ſue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The richeſt beauties (to adorne this Dame)</l>
               <l>In her fayre treaſurie, fetcht Nature thence,</l>
               <l>Which neere vnto diuine perfection came,</l>
               <l>They did ſo much exceed in excellence.</l>
               <l>Shee's beauties ſunne, whoſe beames been fame and praiſe</l>
               <l>Go through &amp; through the world like <hi>Phabus</hi> raies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That beauty was but ſuch (if it was ſuch)</l>
               <l>That carried <hi>Troy</hi> to <hi>Greece,</hi> and <hi>Greece</hi> to <hi>Troy;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Shee's more then fayre, and therefore more then much</l>
               <l>Will be his ioy that once ſhall her enioy.</l>
               <l>But he muſt ſayle, ere he ſuch Hauen gaine,</l>
               <l>Cloſe by the margent of <hi>Caribdis</hi> maine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Her eye loues Arbor is where beauties meete,</l>
               <l>Her cheeke loues garden is where beauties grow:</l>
               <l>Loue walketh there, for there the ayre is ſweet:</l>
               <l>Which alwayes when ſhe breathes doth gently blow.</l>
               <l>Her bluſhing lip, her breath, for ſhew, for ſmell,</l>
               <l>The Roſe exceedes, the Violet doth excell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As many as behold her, doe admire her,</l>
               <l>In beautie, ſhee all beauties doth out-ſtrip,</l>
               <l>All thoughts commend her, and all hearts deſire her:</l>
               <l>Yea, Nature vvonders at her workmanſhippe,</l>
               <l>Admiring her owne skill, and cunning great,</l>
               <l>In framing ſuch a beautie, ſo compleat.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:7"/>
               <l>Nature, another cannot make more fayre,</l>
               <l>Though to that purpoſe all her power were ben't,</l>
               <l>No, though ſhee would from fire, earth, water, ayre,</l>
               <l>Extract the quinteſſence to that ineene.</l>
               <l>For in this Dame there no ingredient lackt,</l>
               <l>That ſhould make beautie perfect and exact.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Had <hi>Iupiter</hi> the earth frequented then,</l>
               <l>When her bright beauty grac't the ſunne-ſhine day,</l>
               <l>Or had this Beauties Patragon liu'd when</l>
               <l>He in the world did wanton, ſport and play.</l>
               <l>O what would he haue done, what not haue done?</l>
               <l>What ſhapes would hee haue tooke her loue t'haue wonne?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Surely he would haue thought her loue a feaſt</l>
               <l>More pleaſing then th'imbracement of his queene;</l>
               <l>And <hi>Iuno's</hi> iealouſie had ſure increaſt,</l>
               <l>If ſhe this peereleſſe princeſſe ſhould haue ſeene.</l>
               <l>For, that his heart was tractable ſhe knew,</l>
               <l>For ſuch attractiue beautie to ſubdue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In this regard ſhe might haue feared much,</l>
               <l>Had this Dames beauty beene to <hi>Ioue</hi> apparrant:</l>
               <l>But the chaſt heart of this chaſt Dame is ſuch,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Inno</hi> might haue tooke it for her warrant.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Diana's</hi> warrant could not be more ſtrong</l>
               <l>Touching her ſelfe, concerning ſuch a wrong.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When <hi>Mars</hi> in <hi>Venus</hi> armes was entertain'd,</l>
               <l>Her breſts diſcloſ'd, her boſome open layde,</l>
               <l>Her deare imbracements had not him reſtrain'd,</l>
               <l>Nor would he in that Circle fayre haue ſtayde.</l>
               <l>Had ſuch a one as <hi>Argentile</hi> paſt by,</l>
               <l>Her face preſented to the War-god's tye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:7"/>
               <l>Her necke, barbreſts, her hand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> legge, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>All coreſpond the beauty of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> face.</l>
               <l>Who would not (might he be prefer'd vntoot)</l>
               <l>With willingneſſe her wand like waſt imbeace,</l>
               <l>And if her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> caſt in a circle were,</l>
               <l>Who would not wiſh himſelfe the Center there.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Had <hi>Hereules</hi> falne into ſuch fayre armes,</l>
               <l>So ſtrong they are (ſtrength in their faireneſſe lyes)</l>
               <l>That though the ſounding trumpets ſhrill alarm's</l>
               <l>Had cal'd him thence to ſome great enterpriſe,</l>
               <l>They would haue held him ſtill, ſtill him detain'd;</l>
               <l>Ah, who could ſtruggle, that were ſo inchain'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Fayrer was ſhe then I haue ſayde ſhe was,</l>
               <l>Nor haue I halfe her beauties worth diſcloſ'd,</l>
               <l>Nor can I door, it did ſo much ſurpaſſe.</l>
               <l>But what is vnexpreſt, let be ſuppoſ'd,</l>
               <l>And as her beauty, ſo her vertues ſhinde;</l>
               <l>Men ioy'd, heauen ioy'd, to ſee her face, her mind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But I muſt leaue her beauty ſo excelling,</l>
               <l>For I would haſt, and therefore ſhun delayes:</l>
               <l>Yet on this theame is ſuch delightfull dwelling,</l>
               <l>That I am loath to leaue her beauties prayſe;</l>
               <l>How ſhe was lou'd, (Loue waites on beauty ſo</l>
               <l>As ſhadow doth on ſubſtance) now ile ſhow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A ſweet young Prince of <hi>Danske</hi> (by fame cal'd forth)</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Curan</hi> he hight; this Prince to <hi>England</hi> came</l>
               <l>To ſee the Dame, whoſe matchleſſe beauties worth,</l>
               <l>Was brought to him vpon the wings of Fame:</l>
               <l>He ſees the Dame, her beautie ſeeth he,</l>
               <l>And prayſeth in his thoughts what he doth ſee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:8"/>
               <l>And though report had ſo extol'd her name,</l>
               <l>And praiſ'd her for ſweet louelineſſe ſo much,</l>
               <l>He findes that Fame but liſpt, and was to blame,</l>
               <l>For (ſeeing her) hee ſee's her beautie ſuch,</l>
               <l>As ſores aboue her prayſe, yea, I may ſay,</l>
               <l>Aboue ſuperlatiue, if beautie may.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And now in him his progreſſe loue beganne,</l>
               <l>From looking, liking, loue from liking grew,</l>
               <l>The ſpacious world could not produce a man,</l>
               <l>That loued with a loue ſo firme, ſo true,</l>
               <l>But for her loue much woe he vnderwent,</l>
               <l>Ere ſhee (vnkind) would to his ſute conſent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This ſweet young louely Prince is ſuch another,</l>
               <l>As was <hi>Adonis</hi> in his greateſt pride:</l>
               <l>This Dame is <hi>Venus,</hi> (that was <hi>Capid's</hi> mother,</l>
               <l>That by <hi>Adonis</hi> was of loue denide:)</l>
               <l>One like that <hi>Adon,</hi> here doth <hi>Venus</hi> loue,</l>
               <l>One like this <hi>Venus</hi> there did <hi>Adon</hi> proue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Not <hi>Clcopatra's</hi> ſonne and daughter fayre,</l>
               <l>Whom their proud ſire the Sunne and Moone did ſtile</l>
               <l>Could match (for beauty) with this princely payre;</l>
               <l>Prince <hi>Curan</hi> to the Princeſſe <hi>Argentile,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Comes neere in comlineſſe, he happy were,</l>
               <l>If ſhe in kindneſſe came, to him as neere.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With <hi>Ganimede</hi> and with <hi>Narciſſus</hi> hee</l>
               <l>May take his place, that were the fairſt of men,</l>
               <l>And with the rateſt ſhe may ranked be,</l>
               <l>That euer yet was prayſ'd by Poets penne,</l>
               <l>How will the world be grac't with beauty ſweet,</l>
               <l>When in their children both their beauties meet.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:8"/>
               <l>Well, he is now in Loue, vp to the heart,</l>
               <l>Yet can hee not obtaine a ſecond view:</l>
               <l>From Princes eyes, and men of high deſart.</l>
               <l>Her iealous Gardian keepes his Neece in miew,</l>
               <l>Betweene the world, and Beauties-ſunne ſo bright</l>
               <l>He interpoſeth clowds, as blacke as night.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Her beauty which doth all mens eyes delight,</l>
               <l>Saue onely his, he ſeekes to keepe vnknowne:</l>
               <l>Leſt Beauties ſame ſhould men of Fame invite,</l>
               <l>To ſeeke her Loue, he wiſheth ſhe had none,</l>
               <l>To ſtop <hi>Fames mouth,</hi> and dim her Beauties beame,</l>
               <l>He therefore ſtriues: but ſtriues againſt the ſtreame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Her beautyes praiſe breakes forth in his deſpight,</l>
               <l>And almoſt like the ayre it ſelfe extends:</l>
               <l>Hee'd ſtop the current hyding her from ſight,</l>
               <l>But ſo her beauty hee the more commends,</l>
               <l>The more ſhee's in her Cloſet kept retyrde,</l>
               <l>The more ſhee's talkt of, and the more admyrde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So quite his endes are croſt, he would ſuppreſſe</l>
               <l>Her beautyes praiſe, but ſee how he miſtakes</l>
               <l>His courſe (though hee intended nothing leſſe)</l>
               <l>Her famous, but himſelfe infamous makes,</l>
               <l>This fact of his, doth more divulge her Fame,</l>
               <l>But to poſteritie records his ſhame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For it directly ſhowes his thoughts are baſe,</l>
               <l>And ſuch as ill beſeeme a boſome Royall:</l>
               <l>Argues him conſcienceleſſe and voyde of grace,</l>
               <l>And prooues him to be periur'd and diſloyall.</l>
               <l>His thoughts, deſires, ambitious, auaritious,</l>
               <l>Vicious his life, his proiects are pernicious.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:9"/>
               <l>O was it not inough (Kinſman vnkind,)</l>
               <l>That he from her ſhould ſo withhold her right,</l>
               <l>But to her chamber ſhe muſt be confinde,</l>
               <l>To ſee, and to bee ſeene doe maides delight;</l>
               <l>But <hi>Aegentile</hi> is hid behind a skreene,</l>
               <l>Shee is not, muſt not, where ſhe would, be ſeene.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But the baſe minded King, to Peaſants baſe</l>
               <l>Admits acceſſe, to noble men denide,</l>
               <l>To view and wooe be grants them time and place,</l>
               <l>And his beſt furtherance affords beſide.</l>
               <l>To marry her to ſome baſe Groome he thought,</l>
               <l>That ſo her right might reſt vnclaim'd, vnſought.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Curan</hi> perceyning this, what did he doe,</l>
               <l>He chang'd his rich attire for baſe aray:</l>
               <l>(O Loue, what ſhifts thou putſt the Prince vnto)</l>
               <l>His name he chang'd, his Titles put away;</l>
               <l>And ſo transform'd himſelfe into a drudge;</l>
               <l>Now if he lou'd or not, the world may iudge.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus liu'd he there, and thus acceſſe he gain'd,</l>
               <l>And on her beauty now his eye hee feedes,</l>
               <l>But in his thoughts full ſore the Prince is pain'd,</l>
               <l>Loue in his breſt a thouſand paſſions breedes:</l>
               <l>And to expreſſe his loue, dumbe ſignes he vſ'd</l>
               <l>He look't, he bluſht, he ſigh'd, he plain'd, he muſ'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>She, whoſe chaſt thoughts euen equall loue reiec't,</l>
               <l>Doth ſee, but will not ſee, his loue vnfit,</l>
               <l>She thinkes it is not worthie of reſpect,</l>
               <l>And therefore will no notice take of it,</l>
               <l>Making a ſhow of pride, though pride ſhe hate,</l>
               <l>Becauſe ſhe knowes pride beſt doth pride abate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:9"/>
               <l>Scarſe knowes ſhe how to looke diſdainefully,</l>
               <l>For neuer pride and ſhe acquainted were;</l>
               <l>Beauty hath got poſſeſſion in her eye,</l>
               <l>And will not ſuffer ſcornefulnes come there,</l>
               <l>Fain would ſhe frown, and yet ſhe knowes not how,</l>
               <l>So calme a ſmoothnes dwels on her fayre brow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When moſt of all ſhee him would terrifie,</l>
               <l>That he ſhould dare to loue, or looke no more,</l>
               <l>Then doth ſhe frowne, ah, but ſo pleaſingly,</l>
               <l>That more he loueth then he lou'd before,</l>
               <l>Between her ſmiles and frowns ſmall ods there lyes,</l>
               <l>for both of them her beauty beautifies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Her frownes cannot her beauty bright obſcure,</l>
               <l>For ſuch ſweet louelineſſe doth them adorne,</l>
               <l>That they entice and powerfully allure,</l>
               <l>Although they argue coynes, pride and ſcorne,</l>
               <l>The more ſhe frownes, the more he loues her ſtill,</l>
               <l>His loue they kindle, though his hopes they kill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>At laſt, loue boyling in his breſt compels him</l>
               <l>Himſelfe and his affection to bewray,</l>
               <l>And craues her loue, but to his griefe ſhe tels him,</l>
               <l>That husbandleſſe ſhe is reſolu'd to ſtay,</l>
               <l>Still ſeeking his ſolicitings to ſhunne,</l>
               <l>So do they ſtill, that ſtill would be vnwunne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When (meeting her) he kindly bids good morrow,</l>
               <l>She ſtrangely doth ſalute him with farewell,</l>
               <l>And ſo his ioy is ouertooke with ſorrow,</l>
               <l>To meete ſeemes heauen to him, to part ſeemes hell:</l>
               <l>Parting which pleaſeth her, doth him diſpleaſe,</l>
               <l>Meeting which he deſires, is her diſeaſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:10"/>
               <l>He ioyes to ſee her, grieues to ſee her coyneſſe,</l>
               <l>Her voyce is heauenly muſicke in his eares,</l>
               <l>Yet are her words vnkind, and make him ioyleſſe,</l>
               <l>Thus are poore Louers toſt t'wixt hopes and feares.</l>
               <l>Twixt care and comfort, paine and pleaſure ſtill,</l>
               <l>So pallats taſte the ſweet diſpleaſing pill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In his aſſumed ſhape he ſtill remaines,</l>
               <l>Nor doth the gentle Lady him diſcloſe:</l>
               <l>He courts her oft, but at her hands he gaines</l>
               <l>Nothing but that that doth augment his woes.</l>
               <l>At laſt (for hearty loue is hard to hide)</l>
               <l>His loue (but not himſelfe) the King diſcride.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>From him to her paſt many an amorous glance,</l>
               <l>Which did his loue vnto the King explaine:</l>
               <l>Glad is the King and doth his ſlaue aduance,</l>
               <l>So to incourage more the ſawcie ſwaine,</l>
               <l>And him prefers vnto promotions high,</l>
               <l>To make the Groome more gracious in her eye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nay, the baſe-minded guilty-thoughted King,</l>
               <l>Himſelfe an interambulator makes,</l>
               <l>That he the match might to concluſion bring,</l>
               <l>The miſer ſpends, and paines the gowtie takes,</l>
               <l>A peaſant for a Princeſſe he would chooſe,</l>
               <l>That he might find the greatneſſe ſhe ſhould looſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>An earneſt Interceſſor to his Neece,</l>
               <l>Still is he, and if he her thoughts may ſway,</l>
               <l>A prize ſurpaſſing far the golden fleece</l>
               <l>Which <hi>Iaſon</hi> gain'd, the baſe muſt beare away.</l>
               <l>Baſe thought he him, the Prince no prince he thought,</l>
               <l>Yet to confer this Iem on him he ſought.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:10"/>
               <l>Should <hi>Edell</hi> now haue knowne for whom he ſpake,</l>
               <l>In whoſe behalfe his arguments he fain'd</l>
               <l>As ſometime greater ſees will Lawyers make,</l>
               <l>To counterplead the cauſe they late maintain'd,</l>
               <l>So had he turn'd (had he the truth diſcride)</l>
               <l>Againſt the Prince, with whom he ſo doth ſide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Lady peſter'd was with his perſwaſions,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Curans</hi> loue, for both vpon her war'd:</l>
               <l>Yet in her breſt they could make no inuaſions,</l>
               <l>For reſolution did her boſome gard,</l>
               <l>That pleads, and this perſwades, &amp; both intreat her,</l>
               <l>Yet all they doe, but makes her griefe the greater.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That <hi>Edell</hi> knowes not <hi>Curans</hi> worth ſhe knowes,</l>
               <l>And yet in his behalfe doth pleade ſo much,</l>
               <l>From hence her griefe, from hence her ſorrow growes,</l>
               <l>This great vnkindneſſe doth her nearely touch,</l>
               <l>That he ſhould hold her in from men of worth,</l>
               <l>And to ſo baſe a match ſhould thruſt her forth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Curan</hi> perceyuing now, his loue offends,</l>
               <l>And that he happy hath no hope to proue,</l>
               <l>He letteth fall his ſute; his wooing ends,</l>
               <l>For (in a ſort his loue doth curbe his loue,</l>
               <l>Becauſe he loues he will not giue offence,</l>
               <l>Therefore (though louing) not his ſute commence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Her beauty breedes his amorous loue, her griefe</l>
               <l>Compaſſionate affection in him breedes,</l>
               <l>And though his loue-ſicke heart doth lacke reliefe,</l>
               <l>Yet he forbeares to ſeeke the ſalue he needes,</l>
               <l>For to that floud he addes (if it hee ſeeke)</l>
               <l>Which her fayre eye diſtils on her fayre cheeke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:11"/>
               <l>His paſſions from his amourous loue do grow,</l>
               <l>But ſuch a bleſſed loue in him is found,</l>
               <l>As makes him to compaſſionate her woe,</l>
               <l>And in his better loue his worſe is drownd,</l>
               <l>His paſſions vrge to proſecute his ſute,</l>
               <l>Compaſſion (thoe) preuayles and makes him mute.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That loue that from his amorous thoughts doth riſe,</l>
               <l>Doth vnto that that pittie breedes giue place,</l>
               <l>Glances and teares goe both from <hi>Curans</hi> eyes,</l>
               <l>Cauſ'd by her beautie and her wretched caſe.</l>
               <l>And ſith his amourous loue her griefe increaſt,</l>
               <l>His tender loue ſo wrought that that loue ceaſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>At leaſt, he cloſe conceal'd it in his breſt,</l>
               <l>What though it ſeem'd to ſcald his heart within,</l>
               <l>In ſignes nor ſyllables he it expreſt,</l>
               <l>For, to augment her griefe he helde it ſinne.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Curan</hi> ſhe hates thy loue, ah cruell ſhee,</l>
               <l>And leſt it moue her, it muſt martyr thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The King now ſees how he his loue reſtraines,</l>
               <l>He ſees it, though to ſee it he is loath:</l>
               <l>For this Apoſtacie put's him to paines</l>
               <l>More then before, for now hee wooes them both:</l>
               <l>He wooeth her to loue, and him to wooe,</l>
               <l>O auarice what putſt thou him vntoo.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Curan</hi> that lou'd the Lady with his ſoule:</l>
               <l>To recommence his ſuite is eaſily brought,</l>
               <l>The aſhes are remou'd, and now the cole</l>
               <l>Is found aliue that dead before was thought:</l>
               <l>They grieue againe the Lady, but in vaine,</l>
               <l>They plow the ſands where there wil grow no grain.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:11"/>
               <l>But why was <hi>Argentile</hi> ſo much vnkinde?</l>
               <l>She knew the Prince, his worth, his Loue, and theſe:</l>
               <l>More powrefull Orators to bend the minde,</l>
               <l>But Women will not loue before they pleaſe.</l>
               <l>She will not, No, ſhe will not loue: and why?</l>
               <l>Becauſe ſhe will not; Women ſo reply.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What a ſtrong hold, ſtrong Reſolution is!</l>
               <l>Where this chaſte Dames chaſt loue immured lyes?</l>
               <l>Not <hi>Danaes</hi> braſen tower, was like to this,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ione</hi> entred there by ſleights and ſubtilties,</l>
               <l>But here a Gard doth euen the key-hole keepe,</l>
               <l>Leſt ſlie inſinuation in ſhould creepe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A Womans will is like to <hi>Danaes</hi> tower,</l>
               <l>Nay, more impregnable is womans will:</l>
               <l>Was neuer man that yet by ſtrength or power,</l>
               <l>Could win this Fort, that force repulſeth ſtill.</l>
               <l>A womans will can neuer be conſtraind,</l>
               <l>Nor can her loue againſt her will be gain'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The will is ſtrong, but yet the ſences weake,</l>
               <l>Weake is the Gard, although the Fortreſſe ſtrong:</l>
               <l>Yet its impoſſible the Gate to breake,</l>
               <l>Or skale the wall, if true themſelues among.</l>
               <l>But lyking-oft, which is Loues Vſher ſlye,</l>
               <l>Gaines entrance here: when flattered is the eye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Therefore wiſe <hi>Ioue,</hi> when he to <hi>Dardan</hi> came,</l>
               <l>Engin, nor inſtrument of war he brought:</l>
               <l>He knew if ſo he ſhould aſſault the ſame,</l>
               <l>He neuer ſhould obtaine the thing he ſought.</l>
               <l>No thundring-wide-mouthd Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>non doth he bring</l>
               <l>Nor Ramme for battrie, nor no ſuch like thing.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:12"/>
               <l>In ſtead of theſe, he brings a Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lars packe,</l>
               <l>Full of fine toyes, that did for ſhew exceed:</l>
               <l>And many a gawd, and many a goodly knacke,</l>
               <l>Which not neceſſitie it ſelfe doth neede.</l>
               <l>Her Female-gard, corrupteth hee with theſe,</l>
               <l>Who fauouring him, he enters there with eaſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For he had pleaſed them ſo well that day,</l>
               <l>That they to lodge him there doe all agree:</l>
               <l>While one vnboults, another turnes the key,</l>
               <l>Ope is the wicket. and in leapeth hee.</l>
               <l>So <hi>Danaes</hi> tower was wonne; and fancies Fort,</l>
               <l>Is neuer wonne, but t'is in ſuch like ſort.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The weakeſt Virgins will is of more ſtrength,</l>
               <l>Then is a gate of ſteele, or wall of braſſe:</l>
               <l>For to compulſion thoſe may yeeld at length,</l>
               <l>This will not be compell'd, nor neuer was.</l>
               <l>But it is ſtrange, that ſtill Prince <hi>Curan</hi> fayles,</l>
               <l>Who by preuailing meanes his Loue aſſayles.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He fittes her humors vaine, he giues her guifts,</l>
               <l>That ſhe may fauor him, he flatters her:</l>
               <l>And to the skye, her praiſes vp he lifts,</l>
               <l>Fore <hi>Hellen's</hi> beautie, he doth hers prefer.</l>
               <l>He grieueth ſore, he ſighs exceedingly,</l>
               <l>He pules, he pines, he tells her he will dye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He prayes, and he perſwades, and all hee ſayes:</l>
               <l>And all he doth, that may be ſaid or done:</l>
               <l>He tryes to winne her Loue a thouſand wayes,</l>
               <l>A thouſand womens loues ſome times are wonne,</l>
               <l>With fewer words, and with far leſſer paines,</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Curan</hi> ſpends, and takes, ere her's he gaines.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:12"/>
               <l>Some winne as ſoone as they beginne to wooe,</l>
               <l>And ſtraight the Clarkes Amen confirmes the match,</l>
               <l>And then to bed, there is no more to doe,</l>
               <l>Yea marry ſir, here is a quicke diſpatch:</l>
               <l>And ſo they ſpeed, when humor ſerues that ſpeake:</l>
               <l>But <hi>Curan</hi> hath a harder ſhell to breake,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nay, of ſo ſtrange a humour, ſome there are,</l>
               <l>That he that loues and loue, for loue deſires,</l>
               <l>Doth (quite vnlike, as Souldiers doe in warre)</l>
               <l>Fayle when he fights, and foyle when he retires.</l>
               <l>So (him that followes it) his ſhadow ſhunnes,</l>
               <l>And followes after him, that from him runnes,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And <hi>Curans</hi> practiſe argu'd that he knew</l>
               <l>This ſecret, for as I haue ſayde before,</l>
               <l>From beauties barre his action he withdrew,</l>
               <l>Yet ſhee to loue inclined nere the more,</l>
               <l>From this ſtrange humour <hi>Argentile</hi> is free,</l>
               <l>It is not vniuerſall then we ſee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſome will ſtifly ſtand in their deniall,</l>
               <l>So that a man would thinke the clocke went true,</l>
               <l>When it (God wot) agrees not with the Dyall,</l>
               <l>As would be ſeene, if thoughts lay ope to view,</l>
               <l>But <hi>Argentile</hi> doth not coyne coyneſſe ſo,</l>
               <l>Her thoughts direct her tongue to anſwere no.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>It fits not here to be Satyricall,</l>
               <l>More of their humours I would elſe reueale,</l>
               <l>And ſith fayre <hi>Argentile</hi> is free from all,</l>
               <l>Her ſexes faults Ile for her ſake conceale:</l>
               <l>As for her coyneſſe, beare with her therein,</l>
               <l>If t'was a fault, why yet t'was not a ſinne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:13"/>
               <l>Her Gardian now perceyuing that intreates,</l>
               <l>Are bootleſſe ſpent as ſtones againſt the winde;</l>
               <l>He now begins to menace her with threates,</l>
               <l>And in his countenance ſhe reades his mind,</l>
               <l>He now no more doth flatter her, but now</l>
               <l>Seekes by compulſiue meanes her will to bow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>They that haue taſted of the like diſtreſſe,</l>
               <l>May iudge of hers, her griefe cannot be ſpoke:</l>
               <l>Yet it ſhe wiſely ſtriueth to ſuppreſſe,</l>
               <l>Leſt elſe her cloſe intendments ſhould be broke.</l>
               <l>But yet ſhee in this Aprill of her yeares,</l>
               <l>Sheds in her cloſet Aprill ſhowers of teares.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Griefes property is beauty to impayre,</l>
               <l>(For beautie's but a caſuall good they ſay)</l>
               <l>But on her face ſo fixed is the fayre,</l>
               <l>That it will not to griefe it ſelfe giue way.</l>
               <l>Through ſorrowes vayle her beauty ſhineth ſo,</l>
               <l>That beauty ſeemeth grac't by beauties foe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Obſeruers might haue reaſon to ſurmiſe,</l>
               <l>(Seeing her lookes ſo louely, yet ſo ſad)</l>
               <l>That ſome ſuch humour did Loues queene ſurpriſe,</l>
               <l>When ſhee (for ſupreme fayre) the verdet had:</l>
               <l>For tis the tuch that doth true beautie trie.</l>
               <l>When in ſad lookes ſweet louelineſſe doth lie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Her griefe ſo well becomes her, that the teares</l>
               <l>Diſtil'd vpon her cheekes, fayre, white and red</l>
               <l>Appeare, as that ſame morning dew appeares,</l>
               <l>Which ſable night on freſheſt flowers hath ſhed,</l>
               <l>Which falling from her cheeke, a man may ſay,</l>
               <l>Her eyes do ſeeme, with pearles to ſtrew her way.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:13"/>
               <l>And ſhe perceyning now what ſmall good will</l>
               <l>Her griple minded Gardian to her beares,</l>
               <l>Fearing conſtraint, or elſe ſome worſer ill,</l>
               <l>She practiſ'd how ſhe might preuent her feares:</l>
               <l>From <hi>Curans</hi> loue, from King, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Court ſhe ſteales,</l>
               <l>While ſhe her ſelfe in ſtrange diſguiſe conceales.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When <hi>Curan</hi> heard ſhe was departed ſo,</l>
               <l>His loue (before the chiefe of his affections)</l>
               <l>Is matcht, nay ouermatched now with woe:</l>
               <l>Reaſon in vaine preſcribes his griefe directions:</l>
               <l>For boundleſſe and confuſ'd his ſorrowes be,</l>
               <l>And after her from Court departeth he.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Lady late, and <hi>Curan</hi> now are gone,</l>
               <l>Blinde loue and fortune blinde leade them aſtray:</l>
               <l>They pace vnuſed pathes to them vnknowne;</l>
               <l>(But ranging rouers cannot looſe their way,)</l>
               <l>Nor know they whereunto theyr iournyes tend,</l>
               <l>Nor when, nor where their Pilgrimage ſhall end.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Vaine findes he his purſuite, and feares as vaine</l>
               <l>His ſute would proue if he ſhould finde his loue,</l>
               <l>From further queſt, he therefore doth refraine,</l>
               <l>And caſt's what courſe is beſt for his behoue.</l>
               <l>To Court hee'l not returne, there is he knowes,</l>
               <l>Dawes, not his Doue, brambles, but not his roſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Long doth the Prince debate, long doth he muſe,</l>
               <l>Long are his buſie thoughts in him at ſtrife,</l>
               <l>Before he doth reſolue what courſe to chuſe:</l>
               <l>At laſt he doth prefer the Shepheards life:</l>
               <l>A flocke, a dogge, a ſheepehooke he prouides,</l>
               <l>Tar-box, and all his implements beſides.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:14"/>
               <l>He, who while in his fathers Court he ſtay'd,</l>
               <l>Was then a Martialiſt although but young)</l>
               <l>Hath chang'd his launce, (for lou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> muſt be obay'd)</l>
               <l>For tooles that to the Shepheards trade belong:</l>
               <l>From warlike <hi>Mars</hi> to ruſticke <hi>Pan</hi> hees ſweru'd,</l>
               <l>But will returne to him that firſt he ſeru'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Tis ſtrange, he in contempt ſhould find content,</l>
               <l>Yet that he found in this deſpiſ'd eſtate,</l>
               <l>Diſgrace the Prince with pleaſure vnderwent,</l>
               <l>For ceaſed is the diſcord and debate</l>
               <l>That was between his thoughts ere they declin'd,</l>
               <l>And thoſe hope croſſing haps to him aſſign'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A brace of yeeres (well pleaſ'd) he thus remaines,</l>
               <l>His thoughts are ſetled, and his mind is free,</l>
               <l>Suiting himſelfe vnto the country Swaines,</l>
               <l>Courtſhip for clowniſhneſſe exchangeth he,</l>
               <l>He that late ſtrooke the Citternes filuer ſtrings,</l>
               <l>Now pipes on oaten ſtrawes, and Iigs he ſings.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Time, griefe, and labour by this time did change</l>
               <l>The Princes thoughts, his Loue is quite forgot:</l>
               <l>His reaſon will not let his loue there range,</l>
               <l>Where can no comfort fall vnto his lot:</l>
               <l>Her abſence, like good Phyſicke to the ſickly,</l>
               <l>Makes him more ſicke at firſt, yet cures him quickly.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Moſt loath was he the ſight of her to looſe,</l>
               <l>For, as fond Patients cheriſh their diſeaſes,</l>
               <l>And will no Phyſicke, if themſelues may chooſe,</l>
               <l>Becauſe perhaps the Pallat it diſpleaſes.</l>
               <l>Her abſence ſo, fit phyſicke for his fit,</l>
               <l>Is forc't on him, ere hee I giue way to it.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:14"/>
               <l>Her fight and preſence he did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>And was vnwilling to forgo the ſame;</l>
               <l>Yet that the ſuell was, maintain'd the fire,</l>
               <l>Cauſing his heart to frie in <hi>Cupids</hi> flame:</l>
               <l>But (that remou'd whereon his harme depended)</l>
               <l>He finds, his ſcorching dog-dayes now are ended.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now ſee the courſe of things, ſayre <hi>Argentile,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who when ſhe left, the Court left not her cares,</l>
               <l>Diſguiſed wanders like a poore exile,</l>
               <l>And with the moſt diſtreſt, diſtreſſe ſhe ſhares:</l>
               <l>Now here, now there, ſhe ſoiourneth a ſpace,</l>
               <l>But yet ſhe findes no certaine biding place.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But now at laſt behold the Princeſſe ſweet,</l>
               <l>Is by a Country Neatheard entertain'd</l>
               <l>To feede his droues, a worke for her vnmeet;</l>
               <l>Yet glad is ſhe, that ſhe the place hath gain'd.</l>
               <l>For here ſhe hopes to find content of mind.</l>
               <l>Which in King <hi>Edels</hi> Court ſhe could not find.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And where feedes ſhee her heards, euen on that plaine</l>
               <l>Where <hi>Curan</hi> (ſhepheard now) his flocks attends,</l>
               <l>See, againſt Deſtenie ſhee ſtriues in vaine:</l>
               <l>Fates haue decreed, ſhe cannot croſſe their ends.</l>
               <l>To that ſame place whereas the Prince abides,</l>
               <l>Some power aboue her owne the Princeſſe guides.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This trickſie Gyrle the ſhepheard ſoone eſpide,</l>
               <l>Like a plaine homely Countrey wench attirde,</l>
               <l>Much did her baſe diſguiſe her beauty hide;</l>
               <l>And yet he ſaw ſo much that he admir'd.</l>
               <l>The more he her admir'd, the more he gaſ'd,</l>
               <l>The more he look't, the more he was amaſ'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:15"/>
               <l>For (viewing her) he thinkes her ſomewhat ſuch</l>
               <l>As <hi>Argentile,</hi> but this her ſtrange diſguiſe</l>
               <l>From that ſhe was hath altered her ſo much,</l>
               <l>Shee's hid behind ſuch darke obſcurities,</l>
               <l>That though his Lady <hi>Argentile</hi> he ſee,</l>
               <l>The ſilly ſhepheard neuer thinkes her ſhe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Though ſo (perhaps) his eye would him perſwade,</l>
               <l>He will not thinke that this is <hi>Argentile,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That ſhe ſhould now profeſſe ſo meane a trade,</l>
               <l>So to conceiue of her, he holds it vile.</l>
               <l>He will not therefore entertaine a thought,</l>
               <l>That this the Lady is that late he fought.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No more dare ſhe giue credits to her eyes,</l>
               <l>For ſeeing him a Shepheard ſo compleat,</l>
               <l>That this ſhould be the man, ſhee'l not ſurmiſe,</l>
               <l>Whom <hi>Edell</hi> ſo aduanc't to honours ſeat.</l>
               <l>Both are deceiu'd, both take their aymes amiſſe,</l>
               <l>Whereof their meaneſſe, the maine reaſon is.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He lou'd, and left, but now he loues a new,</l>
               <l>His loue to <hi>Argentile</hi> he hath forgot,</l>
               <l>And yet to <hi>Argentile</hi> he ſtill is true,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Argentile</hi> he loues, but knowes it not.</l>
               <l>His loue hath found her out, and ſayth tis ſhe,</l>
               <l>But yet opinion ſayth, it cannot be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As <hi>Phaebus</hi> beame when Winter new is fled,</l>
               <l>Reuiues the withered hearbe, and ſapples plant,</l>
               <l>Her beautie ſo reuiues his loue (as dead)</l>
               <l>And giues it life which it did ſeeme to want.</l>
               <l>Now to his loue, ſo withered and decay'd</l>
               <l>Is Iuyce, ſap, life, by beauties beame conuay'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:15"/>
               <l>He that was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a Lord is now a ſwayne,</l>
               <l>Nor that, nor this eſtate from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſecures him:</l>
               <l>For then he lou'd, and now he loues againe.</l>
               <l>A Lady then, a Neatreſſe now, allures him.</l>
               <l>He lou'd her rich, he loues her poore againe,</l>
               <l>Wealth was no four, nor want is now no raine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He notes the Wench, and ſees her beauties rayes,</l>
               <l>Which through ſad clouds of diſcontent ſhine bright,</l>
               <l>Such the new morning in the Eaſt diſplayes,</l>
               <l>Which (through ſom yet left darknes) ſhew their light.</l>
               <l>Beautie he knowes he ſees, but doth not know</l>
               <l>That <hi>Argentile</hi> doth that ſweet beauty owe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Attractiue, pleaſing, powerfull beautie here,</l>
               <l>In him produce their true effects, for why,</l>
               <l>He lookes, he likes, he loues; ſo captin'd were</l>
               <l>His eye, his thoughts, his heart; and now hee'l trye</l>
               <l>If ſhe, whoſe outſide makes ſo fayre a ſhow,</l>
               <l>Beares kindneſſe in her boſome, yea or no.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He frolicke is, his thoughts prognoſticate,</l>
               <l>That he the Laſſes Loue ſhall eaſily winne:</l>
               <l>He thinkes of Loue he doth not dreame of hate,</l>
               <l>He countes her wonne ere he to wooe beginne.</l>
               <l>She cannot chuſe but loue preſumeth he,</l>
               <l>Being (though louely) yet of low degree.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For ſuch preſumption (thoe) himſelfe he check't,</l>
               <l>When doubts into his cogitations came,</l>
               <l>As a raſh Writer doth his worke correct,</l>
               <l>When he with more aduiſe ſurvayes the ſame.</l>
               <l>Now touching Women, he doth thus debate,</l>
               <l>That without reaſon why, they loue and hate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:16"/>
               <l>He thinks how they, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> their humors mou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them.</l>
               <l>Are coy or kind to high or low degree;</l>
               <l>How they that beſt defence, and moſt do loue them,</l>
               <l>Oft times by them the worſt rewarded be:</l>
               <l>And thinkes that he ſhall ſpeed as be ſhall finde</l>
               <l>In her a humour to be coy or kind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With this conceit he ſomewhat calm'd his loue,</l>
               <l>When (looking Eaſtward) downe the hill deſcending,</l>
               <l>He ſpies the Neatreſſe leading forth her Droue,</l>
               <l>Her beautie bright with <hi>Titans</hi> beames contending,</l>
               <l>Which ſight reuiues his loue, and in his breſt</l>
               <l>Such paſſions breedes, as breed his great vnreſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And then he walkes to meet her on the plaine,</l>
               <l>Where vſually ſhe doth her cattell graize;</l>
               <l>To ſhew his loue, and ſue her loue to gaine</l>
               <l>He meanes, admitting now of no delayes:</l>
               <l>But now behold when he is come vnto her,</l>
               <l>(Alas) the ſhepheard faints and feares to wooe her.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Her beauty which allured him to loue her.</l>
               <l>Now makes him fearefull to commence his ſuite,</l>
               <l>Her beautie made him purpoſe now to proue her;</l>
               <l>And now behold her beautie makes him mute:</l>
               <l>For when he ſees her beautie ſo exceeding.</l>
               <l>He feares to ſpeake, becauſe he doubts of ſpeeding.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Beholding her he ſtands, in ſilent pauſe,</l>
               <l>Pleaſ'd is his eye, his thoughts perplexed are,</l>
               <l>For his much looking doth more liking cauſe,</l>
               <l>So is his loue augmented, ſo his care,</l>
               <l>Yet mute he ſtands, for doubts diſmay his mind.</l>
               <l>Leſt beauty make her proud, and pride vnkind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:16"/>
               <l>Why wooes he not, now th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and place doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it,</l>
               <l>Sith ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> that may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wee count halfe wonne?</l>
               <l>He findes acceſſe, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vſe of it,</l>
               <l>To gaine the which the great <hi>Alcides</hi> ſpunne.</l>
               <l>But though long d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>be, at laſt beeſilence breakes,</l>
               <l>And hauing once begunne hee freely ſpeakes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Hee praiſ'd her firſt, but why did hee doe ſo?</l>
               <l>The faire need not be tolde that they are ſuch:</l>
               <l>T'were better they their beautyes did not know,</l>
               <l>For in this point they (Knowledge got too much)</l>
               <l>When <hi>Eue</hi> did taſte the fruite that was denide,</l>
               <l>For this too much infecteth them with pride.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Affection ſure put out his Iudgements eye,</l>
               <l>And made him take a courſe ſo indirect:</l>
               <l>Alas, his leuell quite was laide awrye,</l>
               <l>Praiſe not her beauty whom thou doeſt affect.</l>
               <l>For praiſe ore-ſats their breſts, &amp; then there breeds,</l>
               <l>Pride, ſcorne, diſdaine, and ſuch pernicious weeds.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Some take in vndeſerued praiſe, a pride,</l>
               <l>Who when their haire is like the black-byrds quill:</l>
               <l>Will pleaſed bee to heare themſelues belyde,</l>
               <l>When its compar'd vnto the black-byrds bill.</l>
               <l>Say, <hi>Crowe is white:</hi> they credite all you ſay,</l>
               <l>For their owne thoughts, the parraſites doe play.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But we (the faire) ſhould but commend in thought</l>
               <l>(as Chapmen, not commend what they would buye)</l>
               <l>Let them alone, they neede not to be taught,</l>
               <l>To rate their beauties worths, at priſes high.</l>
               <l>By praiſes their prowd thoughts are higher raiſ'd,</l>
               <l>Who of themſelues are prowd ynough vnpraiſ'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:17"/>
               <l>Well, <hi>curan</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> begins to court his Laſſe,</l>
               <l>And though he Clowniſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> doe now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>:</l>
               <l>Yet neretheleſſe ſome ſhape of that he was,</l>
               <l>His carriage, while he Courts her doth expreſſe.</l>
               <l>Better his geſture, better are his words.</l>
               <l>Then with his clowniſh Shepherds ſhape accords.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Faire neatreſſe, Natures parragon ſaith h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,</l>
               <l>Mine eye, when it thy beauty firſt diſcouer'd:</l>
               <l>Made to my thoughts ſuch faire report of thee,</l>
               <l>that euer ſince about thee they haue houer'd.</l>
               <l>Still will they dwell with thee, for onely there</l>
               <l>Abounds all (in this world) that I hold deare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Adonis</hi> Garden thou to them dooſt ſeeme,</l>
               <l>Where all things pleaſing plenteouſly abound:</l>
               <l>What euer in this world is worth eſteeme,</l>
               <l>Is in this Land of Milke and Honie found.</l>
               <l>For here all ſpices, fruits, and flowers doe grow,</l>
               <l>That wholſome are for vſe, or faire for ſhow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Say, ſhall I ſweete, empale this pleaſng place?</l>
               <l>For my poſſeſſion, I will aske but this:</l>
               <l>Shall I be <hi>Neptune:</hi> and with my imbrace</l>
               <l>Make it an Iland, call't the Ile of bliſſe?</l>
               <l>But to come to the matter now more neerely,</l>
               <l>Belieue it firmely, I doe loue thee dearely.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If gentle kindneſſe ſo adorne thy minde,</l>
               <l>As beautie doth thy Face, then vnto mee</l>
               <l>Thou wilt be pleaſing, debonnaire, and kinde,</l>
               <l>And hope perſwades me thus and thus of thee.</l>
               <l>For it would argue <hi>Nature</hi> much too-blame,</l>
               <l>To giue a cruell-heart ſo faire a frame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:17"/>
               <l>Should, I but call the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ayre, I ſhould the while,</l>
               <l>Seeme from thy glorious beauty to detract.</l>
               <l>Fayre, is for one ſo fayre too low a ſtile,</l>
               <l>To ſhew her ſkill did nature thee compac't.</l>
               <l>Louely thy locks thy forehead more then fayre.</l>
               <l>Thy hayre, thy temples: temples grace thy hayre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If by compariſons I would ſet forth</l>
               <l>The beauty of thy eye, and thy fayre cheeke,</l>
               <l>I cannot finde a Semile of worth,</l>
               <l>Vnleſſe aboue this earth for it I ſeeke.</l>
               <l>Thine eyes doe grace thy face, thy face thine eyes,</l>
               <l>As Skies do grace the Sun, and Sun the Skies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thy beauties natiue are, not like to thoſe,</l>
               <l>That Natures Apes by art doe counterfet,</l>
               <l>Vpon thy cheekes the Lillie and the Roſe</l>
               <l>To ſet the trueſt faireneſſe forth are met</l>
               <l>On thy fayre cheeke is that fayre colour fixt,</l>
               <l>Which their faire colours make together mixt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When thou doſt ſmile, then beauties ſkie is cleare,</l>
               <l>(Such were the ſmiles of louely <hi>Paphos Queene,</hi>)</l>
               <l>When thou doſt bluſh, vpon thy cheekes appeare</l>
               <l>Carnation cloudes, the like ſo ſeldome ſeene,</l>
               <l>That they the world may with amazement ſtrike,</l>
               <l>For great <hi>Olimpus</hi> cannot ſhew the like.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And who? (vnleſſe the aged, dull and dead,</l>
               <l>Whoſe veines and bones do bloud and marrow miſſe)</l>
               <l>Can looke vpon thy lippe, ſo round, ſo red,</l>
               <l>And not deſire to rob it of a kiſſe,</l>
               <l>For, as it hath a power to pleaſe the eye,</l>
               <l>Another tempting ſtrength in it doth lye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:18"/>
               <l>While this he ſpeakes, oft times he changeth hue,</l>
               <l>Now red as bluſhing roſe, now pale againe,</l>
               <l>And when ſhe doth theſe variations view,</l>
               <l>She is confirm'd the ſhepheard doth not faine:</l>
               <l>Of Louers paſſions theſe are ſignes ſhe knowes.</l>
               <l>Therefore ſhe thinkes the ſhepheard doth not gloſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet thus ſhe anſweres, fie, ſayth ſhe, no more,</l>
               <l>Forbeare this idle prayſes to beſtow,</l>
               <l>Vndue to me, a damſell playne and poore,</l>
               <l>Nor is it like that you ſhould beauty know,</l>
               <l>How can a Shepheards ſkill extend to this?</l>
               <l>That ſees it not, nor comes not where it is.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O yes, ſayth he, a ſhepheard ſees the ſkie,</l>
               <l>The Sunne, the Moone, the ſtars a ſhepheard ſees,</l>
               <l>And theſe are beautifull none will denie,</l>
               <l>So then of beautie he may iudge by theſe,</l>
               <l>Whoſe vnmaſk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> beauties lye euen ope to ſwaines,</l>
               <l>Yet fayrer Creatures then the Court containes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>May I not call her fayre, whoſe face I ſee</l>
               <l>The Skie reſemble, ſo me thinks doth thine;</l>
               <l>Saue that in this two Sunnes there ſeemes to be,</l>
               <l>Which thy fayre face ſo grace with their fayre ſhine,</l>
               <l>That ther's no earthly thing that I can name,</l>
               <l>Whoſe beauty comes ſo neare that heauenly frame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thy plainneſſe plainely proues thee fayre, for why,</l>
               <l>Tis the deluding property I know</l>
               <l>Of ornaments and art to mocke the eye,</l>
               <l>By making them ſeeme fayre that are no ſo,</l>
               <l>And of thy beauty, I ſhould haue ſuſpition,</l>
               <l>But that from theſe it taketh no addition.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:18"/>
               <l>And what although thou art of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> degree,</l>
               <l>Yet may thy beauty me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> commendation,</l>
               <l>(Though poore) yet rich in beauty thou mayſt be,</l>
               <l>Is Nature partiall in the diſpenſation</l>
               <l>Of her fayre guiſts, muſt they be needs reſtrain'd,</l>
               <l>Onely to ſuch as fortunes gifts haue gain'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>T'were hereſie to be of this opinion,</l>
               <l>For ſhe is oft as prodigall we ſee,</l>
               <l>Euen to a Begger, as to <hi>Fortunes</hi> minion.</l>
               <l>And ſith her fayreſt gifts haue graced thee,</l>
               <l>May I not prayſe thee, yes, I'me tide vnto it;</l>
               <l>It were detraction if I ſhould not doe it.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When her obiections he had anſwered thus,</l>
               <l>He thus proceedes, O thou art fayre in all,</l>
               <l>I cannot in particular diſcuſſe</l>
               <l>The beauties of thy face, which I may call</l>
               <l>A ſhop of ſeuerall beauties, nay to me,</l>
               <l>Euen beauties little world it ſeemes to be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My necke beneath Loues yoke thy necke hath brought</l>
               <l>It is ſo fayre, ſo ſoft, ſo ſmooth, ſo white,</l>
               <l>Thy lower beauties they are ſeene in thought,</l>
               <l>And in conceit are view'd with much delight.</l>
               <l>Thoſe Iuorie banks (thy breſts) the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thought diſcries</l>
               <l>And Loues ſmooth ſhadie walke that twixt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thought wanders there, &amp; wonders ſtrange diſcouers</l>
               <l>Delightfull wonders, wonderfull delights;</l>
               <l>Ther's no concealing from the thoughts of Louers:</l>
               <l>For all lyes ope to their deepe-ſearching ſights.</l>
               <l>Loues pearcing thought, through all opoſure driues</l>
               <l>And where beſt pleaſing obiects are, ariues.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:19"/>
               <l>The whiteſt colour ſooneſt takes a ſtaine,</l>
               <l>And therefore wonderment it breedes in me,</l>
               <l>That ſtill thy hand ſuch whiteneſſe ſhould retaine,</l>
               <l>Whiteneſſe and it ſure cannot parted be,</l>
               <l>Whiteneſſe and ſoftneſſe which yet neuer fail'd,</l>
               <l>Seeme to thy dainty hand to be intail'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So white, that Lillies are not halfe ſo white,</l>
               <l>So ſoft that Cignets Downe is nothing ſuch,</l>
               <l>The whiteneſſe ſerueth to bewitch the ſight,</l>
               <l>And yet it more inchanteth with the touch,</l>
               <l>And for thy wriſt, the whiteneſſe there is grac't</l>
               <l>By azur'd veines that there are interlac't.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But, to ſet out at full thy beauties prayſe,</l>
               <l>For my performance were a taſke too great,</l>
               <l>Though I about the ſame ſhould ſpend my dayes,</l>
               <l>I could not all thy beauties prayſe repeate.</l>
               <l>How fayre thou art, ſweet wench, I cannot ſhow,</l>
               <l>Nor how much thee I loue, for being ſo.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Little loues he, that can declare how much,</l>
               <l>Lou'd I but ſo, my loue were then but ſmall,</l>
               <l>My loue, ſweet Laſſe, belieue it is not ſuch,</l>
               <l>As can in compaſſe of relation fall:</l>
               <l>As thy much beauty drawes much loue from me,</l>
               <l>Let my much Loue ſome kindneſſe draw from thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Peace, peace, ſayth ſhe, for prayſing me ſo much,</l>
               <l>You in the ayre your breath but idely ſcatter,</l>
               <l>For, (knowing I am neyther ſo nor ſuch,)</l>
               <l>How can I chuſe but know that you but flatter,</l>
               <l>It ſeemes that you ſuppoſe (but you are wide)</l>
               <l>That Ile be pleaſ'd to heare my ſelfe belide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:19"/>
               <l>You almoſt out of breath, your ſelfe haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>In ſeeking prayſeforme (vnworthy farre)</l>
               <l>And rackt your wits, yet all that you haue done,</l>
               <l>But makes me thinke that you a flatterer are,</l>
               <l>And to ſuſpect the ſequell this doth moue me,</l>
               <l>you but diſſemble when you ſay loue me.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O doe not harbour ſuch a thought (ſayth he)</l>
               <l>I doe not flatter, doe not thinke I doe:</l>
               <l>If with my thoughts my words doe diſagree,</l>
               <l>It is becauſe they cannot reach vnto</l>
               <l>That ample height of prayſe and adoration,</l>
               <l>I giue to thee in thought and cogitation.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And for diſſimulation wherewithall</l>
               <l>Thou chargeſt me, O would thou knew'ſt my heart.</l>
               <l>Then thou wouldſt ſoone theſe words of thine recall,</l>
               <l>Wherewith thou blameſt me without deſart,</l>
               <l>And wouldſt (no doubt) aſke pardon with ſubmiſſion</l>
               <l>For this thy ouer haſty raſh ſuſpition.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Such there are ſome, but I am none of thoſe</l>
               <l>That will diſſemble, flatter, lye and fayne,</l>
               <l>If I be ſuch, then mayeſt thou me expoſe</l>
               <l>To thy eternal! hate, and coye diſdayne:</l>
               <l>And let thy kindneſſe ſo with comfort ſtore me,</l>
               <l>As I ſincerely loue thee, and adore thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Fayre maydes by kind are kind, and ſhe doth goe</l>
               <l>A ſtray from her true Nature, I am ſure,</l>
               <l>That is diſdainefull, ſcornefull, proud, or ſo,</l>
               <l>For where ſweet beauty wounds, kindnes ſhould cure:</l>
               <l>But beauty kils, loues arrow ſtriketh dead,</l>
               <l>When ſcornefull pride impoyſoned hath the head.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:20"/>
               <l>Then be not thou (my loue) with pride <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>T'will make thy beauty, tis ſo vile a thing,</l>
               <l>Like vnto pleaſing cates with poyſon taynted,</l>
               <l>For hatefull pride is beauties hurtfull ſting,</l>
               <l>No matter though the beautileſſe be proude,</l>
               <l>But in the fayre pride cannot be allow'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For why, if pride on pleaſing beauty wayte,</l>
               <l>There danger lyes, and we haue cauſe to feare it,</l>
               <l>Elſe pride is but a hooke without a bayte,</l>
               <l>And hurteth none, becauſe ther's none comes neare it.</l>
               <l>Danger becomes more dangerous by bearing.</l>
               <l>A pleaſing forme, not like it ſelfe appearing.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But thy fayre face perſwades me not to doubt,</l>
               <l>In thy fayre boſome much fayre kindneſſe lyes,</l>
               <l>The beames vvhereof through thy faire eyes ſhine out;</l>
               <l>If theſe fayre likelyhoods proue certaineties,</l>
               <l>Fayre hap will crowne fayre hope, and I ſhall then</l>
               <l>Reioyce in my fayre choyce; Fates ſay Amen.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>From out a world of women, thee alone,</l>
               <l>For ſoueraigne of my thoughts doe I ſelect,</l>
               <l>So high a place in my hearts loue hath none,</l>
               <l>As hath thy ſelfe whom onely I reſpect,</l>
               <l>And ſith I loue in no vndue regard,</l>
               <l>The rather let my loue haue due reward.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Reſpect of riches which with moſt beare ſway,</l>
               <l>No motiue is at all, in my Election,</l>
               <l>On Natures, not on fortunes gifts I lay,</l>
               <l>The baſe and groundworke of my firme affection,</l>
               <l>I count thoſe natiue riches thou doſt owe,</l>
               <l>More worth then all that fortune can beſtow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:20"/>
               <l>Yet Riches now a dayes are all in all,</l>
               <l>Wealth goes before, and beautie comes behinde:</l>
               <l>Riches we ſee of Beautie takes the wall,</l>
               <l>To Riches is the higher roome aſſignde.</l>
               <l>Nay like a Cipher is poore beautie thought,</l>
               <l>It muſt be Ioyn'd with wealth, or ſtand for nought.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But I (thou ſeeſt) am of another minde,</l>
               <l>I will not ſuffer ſo my thoughts to erre:</l>
               <l>I am not with the world ſo much declin'de,</l>
               <l>More Fortunes guifts, then Natures to preferre.</l>
               <l>More rich then Mynes of <hi>India,</hi> thou dooſt ſeeme,</l>
               <l>Thy Beauty makes thee ſuch in my eſteeme.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Though <hi>Fortune</hi> blinde, her guifts from thee detaines.</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>Nature</hi> prodigall hath bene to thee:</l>
               <l>Thy For-head, haire, eye, cheeke, lip, necke, Skin, vaines,</l>
               <l>Smooth, bright, gray, faire, red, white, ſoft, blew they be.</l>
               <l>And there doth lye in euery one of theſe,</l>
               <l>A greater power then is in Golde, to pleaſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou need'ſt not: Art not, Richly, proudly deckt,</l>
               <l>Pearles haue no neede to be adorn'd with gold.</l>
               <l>What needs ſupplyment where ther's no defect,</l>
               <l>Or what needſt thou (my Loue) thy locks infold.</l>
               <l>In coſtly Calles of gold, and Laces gay,</l>
               <l>When thy faire treſſes are more rich then they?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet thinke not, (though thy Beautie ſo excell)</l>
               <l>It is too Rich for vſe, and but for ſhow:</l>
               <l>Leſt thou gainſt <hi>Natures</hi> ſacred lawes rebell,</l>
               <l>Not for thy ſelfe doſt thou ſuch Beauty owe.</l>
               <l>Beautie hath not ſuch ſtrong attractiue power,</l>
               <l>To fade vntoucht, like an vngathered flower.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:21"/>
               <l>Nor let thy beauty ſo thy thoughts delude,</l>
               <l>That thou ſhouldſt thinke becauſe thou art ſo fayre.</l>
               <l>The heart of ſome great one ſhall be ſubdude</l>
               <l>To loue, and liſt thee ſo, to honours chayre.</l>
               <l>Waine not for this, let me in this direct thee;</l>
               <l>Left beautie ſade the while, and none reſpect thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Or ſay, that fayre deſert ſhould crowned be,</l>
               <l>And thou for that ſweet beauty thou doſt owe,</l>
               <l>Shouldſt be aduanced vnto high degree:</l>
               <l>Why many haue been rail'd for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eauty ſo,</l>
               <l>Who afterwards with woes acquainted grew.</l>
               <l>Which ere their exaltation ſcarſe they knew.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>On high Eſtates huge heapes of cares attend,</l>
               <l>But ther's contenement in a ſhepheards life,</l>
               <l>Not vs (as them) doth fortune nice offend,</l>
               <l>Diſdaine not then to be a ſheapheards wife.</l>
               <l>Nor am I beggerly, although a Swaine,</l>
               <l>The flocke is mine that mantles yonder plaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Our lowly ſayles are free from enuies guſt,</l>
               <l>We doe not climbe, nor doe we falling feare</l>
               <l>Our ſtates, with winds and waues we do not truſt,</l>
               <l>We haue two certaine harueſts euery yeare,</l>
               <l>By force ſome, ſome by fraud riſe, we by neyther,</l>
               <l>We conſcience, and plaine dealing liue together.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVe liue contented, we at none do grutch,</l>
               <l>The labour our profeſſion doth require,</l>
               <l>Is not perplexiue to the body much,</l>
               <l>Leſſe to the mind, which freely may aſpire,</l>
               <l>Nor is it clog'd with cares, nor is it held</l>
               <l>Downe, as are theirs that great affaires do weld.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:21"/>
               <l>We leaſure and occaſions too do find</l>
               <l>For contemplation, as our flockes we feede,</l>
               <l>Heauen ſtill in fight, is alſo ſtill in minde:</l>
               <l>The Life contemplatiue doth all exceede,</l>
               <l>And neareſt comes for comfort and content,</l>
               <l>To that that ſhall be after this is ſpent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Freſh wholeſome ayre a ſhepheard wanteth not,</l>
               <l>Which many thouſands doe, yet by the ſkies</l>
               <l>He is not perſecuted, when tis hot,</l>
               <l>Some thicke broad branched tree, him canopies:</l>
               <l>VVhoſe green leau'd bowes that largely doe extend,</l>
               <l>VVaft cooling ayre and pleaſing ſhadow lend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And his flockes fleeces cloath him from the cold,</l>
               <l>And arme him gainſt the ſharpeſt Northerne blaſt,</l>
               <l>The pleaſures that we haue are manifold,</l>
               <l>Our troubles ſuch as ſoone are ouerpaſt,</l>
               <l>If thou wouldeſt troubles ſhun, and pleaſurs proue,</l>
               <l>Liue with a ſhepheard, be a ſhepheards loue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I promiſe if thou wilt but pleaſed be,</l>
               <l>My loue with loue, and kindneſſe to repay,</l>
               <l>I will reſigne ſupremacie to thee,</l>
               <l>Doe thou but loue, Ile honour and obey.</l>
               <l>Yea, (were it poſſible) if thou wear't mine,</l>
               <l>My very thoughts ſhould ſuted be to thine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then you ſayth ſhe, no more but loue do craue,</l>
               <l>That which includeth all would you content:</l>
               <l>You but the body of the ſunne would haue,</l>
               <l>VVhence light and heat cannot themſelues abſent,</l>
               <l>VVhat need you more demaund, Loue will not be</l>
               <l>A ſtreamleſſe fountaine, nor a fruitleſſe tree.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:22"/>
               <l>But I am not diſpoſ'd to loue, ſayth ſhe,</l>
               <l>Which if I were, I ſurely ſhould diſdaine,</l>
               <l>You ſhould prepoſterouſly reſigne to me</l>
               <l>That which by right to you doth appertaine:</l>
               <l>Of all d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e offices the chiefe is loue,</l>
               <l>That's the firſt mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er makes the reſt to moue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Not ſo diſpoſd, why doſt thou then propound</l>
               <l>Such bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe (ſaith he) to him that gaines thy loue,</l>
               <l>Making the lougings of my mind abound,</l>
               <l>By ſhewing that thou tractable wilt proue:</l>
               <l>This is as if thou happineſſe ſhouldſt ſhowe,</l>
               <l>Then ſnatch it from me, ſo to worke my woe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thy wordes, to ſhow thy loues worth, thou doſt frame,</l>
               <l>And how much good doth on the ſame depend,</l>
               <l>So kindling my deſires to gaine the ſame,</l>
               <l>While thou the ſame doſt ſo to me commend.</l>
               <l>I hope thou wilt this prayſed ware forgo,</l>
               <l>Though thou art yet diſpoſ'd to anſwere no.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ile buy thy loue, if it be to be ſolde,</l>
               <l>O that I may a happy Chapman proue:</l>
               <l>But it's too precious to be bought with gold,</l>
               <l>What ſhall I giue, Ile giue thee loue for loue:</l>
               <l>And dayly pay, though but in part, for why?</l>
               <l>Thou canſt not haue full payment till I die.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For like as ſpringing fountaines which do owe</l>
               <l>Their ſtreames vnto the ſea, though ſtill they pay,</l>
               <l>Yet ſtill they are in debt, directly ſo,</l>
               <l>Though I ſhall ſtill be paying day by day;</l>
               <l>Yet ſhall I be, euen till I ceaſe to be,</l>
               <l>Thy debt or ſtill, ſtill thou muſt credit me.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:22"/>
               <l>Not all the wealth that <hi>Cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſus</hi> did poſſeſſe,</l>
               <l>Should buy thy loue (if it were mine) from me,</l>
               <l>No greater height of earthly happineſſe</l>
               <l>Deſire I, then to be belou'd of thee</l>
               <l>A prize worth all the world fals to my Lot,</l>
               <l>If thou (to grant thy loue) de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie me not.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Once entertaine me in thine armes, and then</l>
               <l>Ile once be bleſt, in ſpight of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> ſpight:</l>
               <l>And then ile <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ell the world, if tongue or penne</l>
               <l>Can giue expreſſure to ſo much delight.</l>
               <l>What thy imbracements yeeld, what Ioy, what bliſſe,</l>
               <l>But when, ah when ſhall I diſcourſe of this?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oh, hold not from me that felicitie,</l>
               <l>Which they afford, that do afford their loues,</l>
               <l>And with their loues a multiplicitie</l>
               <l>Of pleaſutes and delights; ſure it behoues</l>
               <l>That thou propound ſuch for thing Imitation,</l>
               <l>That anſwere thus the end of their Creation.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Good, now no more, I cannot loue ſaith ſhe,</l>
               <l>Againſt the Hayre then vrge me not vntoot,</l>
               <l>Excuſe me (tho) the fault is not in me,</l>
               <l>My ſtarres were oppoſite, I cannot door.</l>
               <l>Thus puts ſhe off her fault, and ſhewes the while,</l>
               <l>A fault deriu'd from <hi>Eue</hi> to <hi>Argentile.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Shee will not loue, yet leſt he thinke her wilfull,</l>
               <l>She anſweres thus, ſhe cannot loue ſhe ſayes,</l>
               <l>And as ſhe were in conſtellations skilfull,</l>
               <l>Her humours fault vpon the ſtarres ſhe layes:</l>
               <l>But <hi>Curan</hi> though this anſwere makes him doubt,</l>
               <l>Will not for this repulſe of hers giue out.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:23"/>
               <l>Your ſtarres, ſaith he, tuſh, hold not this opinion:</l>
               <l>Admit the chaſteſt of them <hi>(Luna)</hi> raign'd,</l>
               <l>Did not I pray thee <hi>Luna,</hi> Ioue <hi>Endimion,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And was not ſhe with loues ſweet paſſions pain'd,</l>
               <l>yes <hi>Luna's</hi> ſelfe did loue, elſe Poets faine,</l>
               <l>Then how can <hi>Luna's</hi> influence loue reſtraine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No, I not feare the enmitie of thoſe,</l>
               <l>Be thou but willing, I deſire but this,</l>
               <l>They cannot my wiſh't happineſſe oppoſe,</l>
               <l>Nor be a barre to my deſired bliſſe.</l>
               <l>Let churliſh and malignant ſtarres repine,</l>
               <l>I care not; ſo thy will to loue incline.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Therefore as erſt I ſayd, I ſay againe,</l>
               <l>Giue pride no place I pray thee in thy breſt,</l>
               <l>Away with ſoornefulneſſe and coy diſdaine,</l>
               <l>Which moſt do plague the kindeſt men and beſt,</l>
               <l>For the beſt natures ſtill moſt ſubiect be,</l>
               <l>To loue-ſicke paſſions (moſt in this agree.)</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As thou art fayre, ſo be thou kind my deare,</l>
               <l>Should pride (which heauen forbid) contracted be</l>
               <l>To thy ſweet beautie, it would cauſe (I feare)</l>
               <l>A ſeparation twixt my ioyes and me.</l>
               <l>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> kindneſſe from thy beautie thou ſhouldſt ſeuer,</l>
               <l>My ioyes and I are then diuerſt for euer.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As beautie doth, euen ſo let mercy reſt</l>
               <l>In thy fayre eye, for theſe are two fayre twins:</l>
               <l>Denie not lodging to ſo kind a gueſt:</l>
               <l>At that ſayre ſigne where her faire ſiſter Innes,</l>
               <l>Beauties kind ſiſter muſt keepe with her ſtill,</l>
               <l>Elſe where ſhe conquers, cruelly ſhee-l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:23"/>
               <l>Thus ſtill hee pleades, and though ſhee ſtill withſtand:</l>
               <l>Yet doth not his affection change or varrie:</l>
               <l>For why? his loue is winnowed, clenſ'd, and fan'd,</l>
               <l>No light inconſtant chaffe with it doth tarrie.</l>
               <l>In vaine doth ſhe denie, for ſtill he tries,</l>
               <l>In vaine he tries her, for ſhe ſtill denies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What bootes it her, although her tongue denie,</l>
               <l>Forbidding loue, refuſing loue to grant:</l>
               <l>Sith the meane while her lip, her cheeke, her eye</l>
               <l>Plant that, which ſhe endeuours to ſupplant:</l>
               <l>Her tongue forbids, her beautie bids againe,</l>
               <l>Loue yeelds to louelineſſe, and words are vaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Though ſhe her name, her ſtate, her tire, her traine,</l>
               <l>Had ſo diſmiſt, caſt off, forgone, and chang'd,</l>
               <l>Yet her owne thoughts ſhe ſtill doth entertaine.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Curan</hi> had ſped if they had beene eſtrang'd:</l>
               <l>They told her ſhe that lately did diſdaine</l>
               <l>A Princes loue, now muſt not loue a Swaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Of all her outward worth with her remaines</l>
               <l>Onely her beauty, all the reſt is gone,</l>
               <l>But that by lawfull meanes ſhe ſtill maintaines,</l>
               <l>And blame her not if ſhe preſerude her owne.</l>
               <l>Rather blame them (if ſuch be to be found)</l>
               <l>That lay dead colours on a liuely ground.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Her beauty will abide the touch, tis true,</l>
               <l>Her louely cheekes haue beauties dye in graine;</l>
               <l>For they their ſweet eye-pleaſing natiue hue,</l>
               <l>In ſpight of <hi>Phaebus</hi> fierie eye retaine:</l>
               <l>Her beautie hath a ſtrange rare qualitie,</l>
               <l>Subiect to nothing but mortality.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:24"/>
               <l>And it is <hi>Curans</hi> hungry eye's repaſt,</l>
               <l>Yea and a pleaſing diſh to it indeed,</l>
               <l>And fith when ſhe is abſent it muſt faſt,</l>
               <l>When ſhe is preſent it doth frankly feede,</l>
               <l>To it that can (with faſting) not away,</l>
               <l>A Lent in length ſeemes euery faſting day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Officiouſly heſerues his miſtreſſe coy,</l>
               <l>He runs for her, he helps her guide her drone,</l>
               <l>Proud is the Prince if ſhe will him imploy,</l>
               <l>See here the power and potencie of loue:</l>
               <l>Her for no better then ſhe ſeemes he takes,</l>
               <l>yet willingly himſelfe her ſlaue he makes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And if ſhe doe but daigne him one kind looke,</l>
               <l>Quite ouerpayde he holds himſelfe to be,</l>
               <l>For all the paines that he for her hath tooke,</l>
               <l>So pleaſed with a gentle looke is he:</l>
               <l>And on her ſmiles and frownes doth he attend,</l>
               <l>As life and death did on her lookes depend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As fares it with a ſhip toſt on the maine,</l>
               <l>When windes and waues conſpire her ouerthrow:</l>
               <l>Shee's hoyſed vp, and then caſt down againe.</l>
               <l>From tops of liquid mounts, with <hi>Curan</hi> ſo,</l>
               <l>Her ſmiles do hoyſe his hopes into the ayre,</l>
               <l>Her frownes do beat them down beneath deſpaire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet not her ſmiles, his hopes do him beguile,</l>
               <l>For he his hopes doth from miſtaking take:</l>
               <l>She but derides his folly with a ſmile,</l>
               <l>Which he an argument of loue doth make.</l>
               <l>Alas for him, how deſperate is his ſtate,</l>
               <l>When his beſt ſignes of loue, are ſignes of hate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:24"/>
               <l>Well, let him reſt content though thus forlorne,</l>
               <l>And not repine, though now he pine and droope:</l>
               <l>He ſhall (ere long) enioy a Princeſſe borne,</l>
               <l>But the high towring Eagle will not ſtoope</l>
               <l>To the baſe Kite, nor ſhe to him, till hee</l>
               <l>(Being vnvaild) a Peaſont ceaſe to be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But her deare Loue, he firſt muſt dearely buye,</l>
               <l>T'will coſt him many a ſigh and many a teare,</l>
               <l>That hauing bought it at a price ſo high,</l>
               <l>Accordingly, he then may holde it deare.</l>
               <l>The more is now his griefe, and his annoy,</l>
               <l>When ſhee is his, the more will be his ioy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Leander</hi> kinde, as hee to <hi>Her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> went,</l>
               <l>The paines hee tooke, the perills that hee paſt,</l>
               <l>The more they were, the more was his content,</l>
               <l>VVhen in his weary armes he her imbrac't.</l>
               <l>So when Prince <hi>Carans</hi> preſent ſufferings ceaſe,</l>
               <l>They (to his future Ioyes) ſhall giue increaſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Well may he, while he hath her Ioue in chace,</l>
               <l>Endure the worſt that Fortune can inflict:</l>
               <l>For <hi>Fates</hi> haue mark't her his, though for a ſpace,</l>
               <l>His Fortune ſeemes his <hi>Fate</hi> to contradict.</l>
               <l>And now the more he ſuffers for her ſake.</l>
               <l>The more ſhall he of comfort then pertake.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Shee muſt be his, but yet ſome miſerie,</l>
               <l>For her deare ſake he muſt endure before:</l>
               <l>That Ioyes (ſucceeding griefe their contrarie,)</l>
               <l>May to his apprenenſion ſeeme the more,</l>
               <l>But that ſhe ſhall be his, did hee but knowe,</l>
               <l>Then in his boſome were no place for woe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:25"/>
               <l>But this, he doth not know; nay, there is throwne</l>
               <l>So thicke a miſt before his iudgements-eye:</l>
               <l>That ſhe her ſelfe is ſtill to him vnknowne,</l>
               <l>Though he be daylie in her companie.</l>
               <l>He muſt not know her his, nor know her neither,</l>
               <l>Till hee (twiſe happie then) know both together.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Daylie, as duely as hee goes to fielde,</l>
               <l>He Courts his wench, but not at all preuailes:</l>
               <l>Yet ſtill he hopes that ſhee at laſt will yeelde,</l>
               <l>Therefore he plyes her ſtill, but ſtill he failes,</l>
               <l>One day at laſt beneath a ſhady tree,</l>
               <l>He cloſely ſiding her, thus pleadeth he.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Why art thou ſtill vnkinde, why cruell ſtill?</l>
               <l>Why is thy breſt ſo empty of remorſe?</l>
               <l>My heart thou mayſt with thy vnkindneſſe kill,</l>
               <l>But thou canſt not diuert Loues conſtant courſe.</l>
               <l>Still doe I loue, though ſtill thou doeſt diſdaine me,</l>
               <l>Beauty doth ſo perſwade: nay, ſo conſtraine mee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My Loue, if it but ordinary were,</l>
               <l>Mixt with a negligent indifferencie:</l>
               <l>Why thy vnkindnes then I well could beare,</l>
               <l>Nor could it once ſo much as trouble mee.</l>
               <l>Some cannot loue vntill they kindneſſe finde,</l>
               <l>Nor longer then their Loues continue kinde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He that loues ſo, (nor are ſuch Louers ſtrange)</l>
               <l>Can ſport at her that falſly doth deceyue:</l>
               <l>Smile at the change, if ſmiles to frownes do change,</l>
               <l>Loue while ſhee loues, and leaue when ſhe doth leaue.</l>
               <l>T'is harmleſſe Loue, on kindnes that depends,</l>
               <l>To loue the vnkinde, that's the loue offends.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:25"/>
               <l>This I finde true, yet hopefully ſuppoſe</l>
               <l>Thou bearſt not ſuch an vnrelenting minde:</l>
               <l>But that thou wilt compaſſionate my woes,</l>
               <l>And wilt not proue eternally vnkinde,</l>
               <l>While thy vnkindnes wounds my mind with griefe.</l>
               <l>Hope of redreſſe is all my hearts reliefe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My Loue with thy vnkindnes long hath ſtriu'd,</l>
               <l>Except theſe proue to be of equall ſtrength:</l>
               <l>Well may I hope my griefe is not long liu'de,</l>
               <l>For one of theſe will ſure be foyl'd at length.</l>
               <l>When eyther ſhall be foyl'd and ouerthrowne,</l>
               <l>Then ends my griefe and ſad lamenting-mone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Till or my Loue, or thy vnkindneſſe ceaſe,</l>
               <l>Needs muſt my griefe and languiſhment ſtill laſt:</l>
               <l>It is not poſſible I ſhould finde eaſe,</l>
               <l>Till I can eyther ſay the fit is paſt.</l>
               <l>Or till thou doeſt my Loue with Loue repay,</l>
               <l>Which would to thy vnkindneſſe not giue way.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But that my Loue will ceaſe, and ſo my woe,</l>
               <l>I haue ſmall hope, though ſtill vnkinde thou proue:</l>
               <l>I know my I oue more laſting is then ſo,</l>
               <l>Nor is it fit that wee by fittes ſhould Loue.</l>
               <l>Then all my hope of comfort doth depend</l>
               <l>On this, that thy vnkindnes once will end.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then when deſire my Fantaſie doth ſway</l>
               <l>Such as I wiſh thou art to it preſented:</l>
               <l>My Loue with Loue, me thinkes thou doeſt repay,</l>
               <l>And from thy vnkinde ſelfe thou ſeem'ſt abſented.</l>
               <l>But when I wake, thy kindneſſe is away,</l>
               <l>No longer then I dreame, my Ioyes will ſtay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:26"/>
               <l>To finde thee kinde thus in my idle Dreames,</l>
               <l>What Comfort in thy kindneſſe ly'es doth ſhow:</l>
               <l>Whereby my woes wax on to worſe extreames,</l>
               <l>That good I muſt not taſt, I would not know.</l>
               <l>So to the damned ſoule in hell, that is</l>
               <l>Hell's, the more hell, becauſe he knowes ther's bliſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And though I know that Dec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mes are idle fictions,</l>
               <l>And that they much in them do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ldome carry:</l>
               <l>But ſtill ſuccede like <hi>Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>anackes Prodictions,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVhich tell how winde and weathers ſtate will varrie.</l>
               <l>Kindneſſe to come, they promiſe (tho) in thee,</l>
               <l>And comfort in reuerſion ſo to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet they perhaps doe but delude m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (tho,)</l>
               <l>And do no more but ſeeme to promiſe this:</l>
               <l>Then is my hope but vaine, if this be ſo,</l>
               <l>And that (I catch) but Comforts ſhaddow is,</l>
               <l>Feare doth conſound the hope that hence doth riſe,</l>
               <l>Sith Dreames are but ſuch meere incertainties.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Diſdaine to mee is like infectious ayre,</l>
               <l>As that of health, ſo this of hope depriues:</l>
               <l>As that diſeaſe, ſo this doth breed diſpaire,</l>
               <l>Yet againſt that there are preſeruatiues.</l>
               <l>But none gainſt this, diſdaine the heart doth kill,</l>
               <l>Euen in diſpight of Drug and Doctors skill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus pules the Prince, and thus doth he complaine,</l>
               <l>Euen melted with the Sun-ſhine of her eye:</l>
               <l>Nor can his manly heart the ſtroke ſuſtaine,</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Cupids</hi> Childiſh-dart, fie <hi>Curan,</hi> fie.</l>
               <l>From a weake womans Fading-beauty, hee</l>
               <l>Deriues his ſtrength, yet he hath foyled thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:26"/>
               <l>And is it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ding beauty ſhould be of ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch force</l>
               <l>The nature of this Impe of <hi>Mars</hi> to change,</l>
               <l>And from his warlike Patron him diuo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce.</l>
               <l>T'is ſtrange, yet beauty hath this ſeace affected,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the which he hath himſelfe ſubiected.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Beauty be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itcheth him, and makes him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ote,</l>
               <l>Then Che<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ltie be ceaſeth to purſue:</l>
               <l>Himſelfe to <hi>Cupid</hi> ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ice to denote;</l>
               <l>To <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Martiall</hi> feates he bids adue.</l>
               <l>But when he ſhall his Ladyes loue obtaine</l>
               <l>The warlike Prince will be himſelfe againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But (yet) ſhe him denyes and anſwereth thus,</l>
               <l>Do you not thinke my wayes are negatiues:</l>
               <l>Scarce are they ſo indeede in ſome of vs,</l>
               <l>Scandall too-much from ſuch, our ſelues deriues.</l>
               <l>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> doe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot thinke me ſuch, ſuch am not I,</l>
               <l>I hate the tongue that doth the thoughts belye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I alwayes ſtrongly haue oppos'de your tryalls,</l>
               <l>Not like to her that yeeldingly denyes:</l>
               <l>I wrap not vp conſent in nice denyalls,</l>
               <l>Nor haue I prun'd your hopes with my replyes.</l>
               <l>But rather to ſupplant them I haue ſought,</l>
               <l>For I to yeeld to Loue, will not be brought.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Such were her words, her thoughts were alſo ſuch,</l>
               <l>She doth not loue, ſhe meaneth to loue neuer:</l>
               <l>But on her ſtrength ſhe doth relye too-much,</l>
               <l>For in her power it is not to perſeuer.</l>
               <l>Strong is her reſolution, yet too-weake,</l>
               <l>The high diſpoſers purpoſes to breake.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:27"/>
               <l>You doe (ſayth ſhe) but vaine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>While thus you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> loue with worth,</l>
               <l>Loues Harbeng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſtill enters by the eye,</l>
               <l>Small comfort kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>king at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> affordes,</l>
               <l>For till the eye let liking in, the breſt</l>
               <l>Nere lodgeth L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, that thought diſturbing gueſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſe therefore thus to ſpend your breath in vaine,</l>
               <l>Auert your Loue, becauſe you are not lou'd,</l>
               <l>Loue not where Loue for Loue you cannot gaine:</l>
               <l>Let your ill placed liking be remou'd:</l>
               <l>Shut in your wandring eye, your thoughts reſtraine,</l>
               <l>Refuſe to giue your raſh deſires the raine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus counſels ſhe, yet courts he her againe,</l>
               <l>But cannot (tho) her reſolution ſhake:</l>
               <l>Onely her eares his words doe entertaine:</l>
               <l>But to her heart they no intruſion make.</l>
               <l>Nor feares, nor ſhuns ſhe his aſſaults, for why?</l>
               <l>On her approued ſtrength ſhe dare relye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>From his aſſaults ſhe held her ſelfe alooſe</l>
               <l>At firſt, but now ſhe doth not feare nor doubt,</l>
               <l>Againſt Loues darts ſhe thinks her breſt is prooſe,</l>
               <l>Becauſe that it ſo long hath held them out:</l>
               <l>Yet oportunitie the Prince doth fayle,</l>
               <l>Nor can his importunity preuaile.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But now behold, when ſhe to Loue thinkes leaſt,</l>
               <l>And thinks her ſelfe beſt able to withſtand,</l>
               <l>And now his hopes that languiſht are deceaſt:</l>
               <l>Now Loue himſelfe doth take his cauſe in hand,</l>
               <l>Diſpayre makes <hi>Curan</hi> now leaue off to wooe her,</l>
               <l>yet wins her as he tels his fortunes to her.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:27"/>
               <l>Growne deſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> now, he thus to her complain'd,</l>
               <l>Of all mens Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>mes mine is ſure the worſt,</l>
               <l>Thus twiſe to loue, and twiſe to be diſdai'nd.</l>
               <l>Ah Wretch, was euer man ſo much accurſt,</l>
               <l>Loue that imparadi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth ſome, to me</l>
               <l>Giues hell it ſelfe, if hell on earth there be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pigm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lion</hi> was more bleſt then I, for he</l>
               <l>Succeſfully, an Iuorie Image lou'd,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> wrought miracles for him, but ſhe</l>
               <l>Is deafe to my intreates, ſhee'l not be mou'd</l>
               <l>To turne to fleſh that flintie heart of thine,</l>
               <l>And to reioycings theſe complaints of mine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Loue vnto ſome much happineſſe doth bring,</l>
               <l>But vnto me it bringeth nothing leſſe,</l>
               <l>My Loue's a bitter root from whence doth ſpring</l>
               <l>Anguiſh, griefe, ſorrow, woe and wretchedneſſe,</l>
               <l>And that I twiſe ſhould loue the Fates haue caſt,</l>
               <l>And ſo ſhould twiſe theſe helliſh torments taſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Shee that firſt cauſ'd my anguiſh and my ſmart</l>
               <l>Was fayre like thee, and thou vnkind as ſhee,</l>
               <l>She had thy beauty, and thou haſt her heart,</l>
               <l>Shee tooke, thou tak'ſt, my ioyes, my life from me.</l>
               <l>I lou'd, I loue, in both vnhappy I,</l>
               <l>I languiſht then, but now for loue I die.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Neatreſſe (yet vnſatiſſide) enquires</l>
               <l>What wench it was he firſt affected ſo:</l>
               <l>He (vrdg'd to ſpeake of her) his bloud retires,</l>
               <l>Pale were his lookes, ſcarſe could he ſpeake for woe.</l>
               <l>T'was <hi>Argentile,</hi> ſo much admir'd, ſayth he,</l>
               <l>Onely in ſtate an ouermatch to thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:28"/>
               <l>Did you, ſaith ſhe, know that young Lady fine,</l>
               <l>I did, ſayth he, and dearely I her loud:</l>
               <l>She was my Saint, I offered at her ſhrine</l>
               <l>Teares, vowes and ſighes, and for her ſake I prou'd</l>
               <l>A torment worſe then death it ſelfe can be,</l>
               <l>And now a torment worſe then that for thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>At <hi>Kirkland</hi> in my Fathers Court, my dayes</l>
               <l>In ſweet content I ſpent, vntill mine eare</l>
               <l>Was filde with <hi>Argentiles</hi> ſweet beauties prayſe,</l>
               <l>But then could I no longer tarry there,</l>
               <l>I came to ſee, I ſaw, I lou'd, and ſo</l>
               <l>(For luckleſſe was my loue) began my woe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And then (for the vngentle King denide</l>
               <l>Acceſſe to Noble men of note and fame)</l>
               <l>Forthwith my dignities I doft aſide,</l>
               <l>And for her ſake a Peaſant I became,</l>
               <l>And by that meanes acceſſe I did obtaine,</l>
               <l>Yet miſt my end, her loue I could not gaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I did as much as hearty loue could doo,</l>
               <l>To gaine her loue, but ſtill was ſhe vnkind:</l>
               <l>The King himſelfe in my behalfe did wooe,</l>
               <l>Yet my intreats, with vrgings his, combinde,</l>
               <l>Were ſtill ſucceſſeſſe, for ſhe ſtill denide,</l>
               <l>So ſtill I dying liu'd, and liuing dyde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No thought, no inſtigation of new loue,</l>
               <l>Since her I loſt did enter once my breſt,</l>
               <l>Vntill thine eye, that would dull <hi>Saturne</hi> moue,</l>
               <l>Replanted loue, and robd me of my reſt:</l>
               <l>Thy powerfull beauty ſhouldered all a ſide.</l>
               <l>That Loues reentrance hindered or de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>'e.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:28"/>
               <l>With my new Loue (alaſſe) began new woes,</l>
               <l>For nothing elſe but griefe and wretchedneſſe,</l>
               <l>Doth hapleſſe, hatefull loue on me impoſe:</l>
               <l>But death I hope, ere long will giue redreſſe.</l>
               <l>Far off is comfort, but deſpayre is nigh,</l>
               <l>Ah then why doe I not deſpayre and dye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nay ſtay, ſayth ſhe, and tell me firſt your name,</l>
               <l>Your own true name which you haue chang'd I know.</l>
               <l>I haue quoth he for loue, but not for ſhame,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Curan</hi> is my name, the truth is ſo:</l>
               <l>Then griefe her heart, &amp; teares her eyes ore-filde,</l>
               <l>And down her cheekes ſome chriſtall drops diſtild.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He wept to ſee her weepe, and aſkt the cauſe,</l>
               <l>Wherefore ſhe did that precious liquor ſpill,</l>
               <l>And why ſhe ſigh'd, and why ſhe ſo did pauſe.</l>
               <l>Yet ſtill ſhe wept, ſtill ſigh'd, and muſed ſtill.</l>
               <l>He ſeeing this, with her will partner be,</l>
               <l>He wept, he ſigh'd, he mul'd, as wel as ſhe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>His wonder was, to ſee her wonder ſo,</l>
               <l>His ſorrow was to ſee her ſorrow ſuch,</l>
               <l>She muſ'd he ſhould his loue ſo twiſe beſtow,</l>
               <l>She grieu'd that ſhe had made him grieue ſo much.</l>
               <l>Thus they doe now each others harmes condole,</l>
               <l>And ſympathize as both had but one ſoule.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>At laſt ſhe ſpake, the words that from her went,</l>
               <l>Bore comfort with them on theyr ayrie wings:</l>
               <l>And euery Meſſenger that ſo ſhe ſent</l>
               <l>To <hi>Curans</hi> eare, a ioyfull burthen brings,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Curans</hi> eare neere bleſt vntill that day,</l>
               <l>Doth their deare preſent to his heart convay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:29"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ran,</hi> quoth ſhe, the Fort you ſought to winne,</l>
               <l>With this laſt battrie is ſo ſore diſtreſt,</l>
               <l>That now the Gate is ope to let you in:</l>
               <l>Be happy, if my loue can make you bleſt,</l>
               <l>Your twiſe beloued <hi>Argentile</hi> is yours,</l>
               <l>In weale and woe, ſo long as life endures.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The pallat vſ'd to bitter taſtes we ſee,</l>
               <l>Can ſweetneſſe at the firſt ſcarſe well en dure;</l>
               <l>His eyes with light at firſt offended be,</l>
               <l>That long hath line in dungeon deepe obſcure,</l>
               <l>So <hi>Curan</hi> vſ'd to griefe and ſad lamenting,</l>
               <l>Offended is with ioy, at firſt preſenting.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As he that (ſleeping) doth illuſions ſee</l>
               <l>So fearefull, that for dread thereof he quakes,</l>
               <l>Seeming to be in dangers ſuch that he</l>
               <l>Feeles fear's impreſſion, ſtill when he awakes:</l>
               <l>So <hi>Curan</hi> fares, free from his ſeares hee's ſet,</l>
               <l>But cannot apprehend his ſafety yet.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But now by this he finds his Ioyes to be</l>
               <l>True and ſubſtantial, though he late did feare,</l>
               <l>(So much tranſported from himſelfe was he)</l>
               <l>That they deluſiue and fantaſticke were,</l>
               <l>But now the ſunne of comfort ſhines out bright,</l>
               <l>And feares and griefes, like miſts are put to flight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Like as with him that in his ſleepe doth proue,</l>
               <l>That ſtrange diſeaſe, feeling vpon his breſt</l>
               <l>A deadly waight which he would faine remoue,</l>
               <l>But ſtriues in vaine, till he awakt, finds reſt.</l>
               <l>With <hi>Curan</hi> ſo it far'd, and ſo it fares</l>
               <l>Oppreſſed with, and eaſed of his cares.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:29"/>
               <l>He would expreſſe his hearty ioy, yet long</l>
               <l>He like a ſenſeleſſe ſtatue ſtandeth mute,</l>
               <l>Ioy doth ſo ouerwhelme him that his tongue</l>
               <l>Cannot as yet this office execute:</l>
               <l>So when the heart is drown'd in ſorrowes deepe,</l>
               <l>The eye (we ſee) oft times forgets to weepe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And much ſhe ioy'd, though not in ſo much meaſure:</l>
               <l>Yet in this extaſie a part ſhe beares:</l>
               <l>Now happy mutuall loue produceth pleaſure,</l>
               <l>Feares are remou'd, ceaſed are ſighs and teares:</l>
               <l>The worſe dependants now are baniſht quite,</l>
               <l>And on their loue attendeth ſweet delight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What helliſh torments doth that man endure,</l>
               <l>That coyly findes his hearty loue reiected:</l>
               <l>Againe, if earth yeeld ioy, he taſtes it ſure,</l>
               <l>That dearely loues, and dearely is affected.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Curan,</hi> late as the firſt, now as the laſt,</l>
               <l>Seemes ſnatcht from <hi>Limbo,</hi> and in <hi>Eden</hi> plac't.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When to himſelfe, him Ioy and Wonder left,</l>
               <l>He ſayd, and are you <hi>Argentile</hi> my deare:</l>
               <l>In happy time was I of you bereft,</l>
               <l>That I thus happily might find you here.</l>
               <l>Twiſe bleſt may I my new bleſt knowledge call,</l>
               <l>I know you now, and know you mine withall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A thouſand griefes this heart of mine haue grip't.</l>
               <l>By your vnkindneſſe cauſ'd, that your conſent,</l>
               <l>Hath them away (as they had nere been) wip't.</l>
               <l>And in their place hath planted ſweet content,</l>
               <l>O happy ſuffrings, whereupon depends</l>
               <l>Such happie Iſſue, and ſuch bleſſed ends.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:30"/>
               <l>By this her heart with <hi>Cupids</hi> dart is thrild,</l>
               <l>Her coyneſſe earſt, is turn'd to kindneſſe now,</l>
               <l>With Loues ſweet malladie her breſt is ſide,</l>
               <l>And many fauours ſhe doth him allow:</l>
               <l>Now ſtrangeneſſe being baniſht for his ſake,</l>
               <l>She frankly giues what ſhe refuſ'd to take.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O what a Metamorpheſis is this,</l>
               <l>That here is wrought: this D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſell but of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>Would ſcarſly for a Kingdome giue a kiſſe,</l>
               <l>Which now ſhe vallues at an eaſie rate.</l>
               <l>Her kindneſſe was exceeding meane indeed,</l>
               <l>But now almoſt it doth all meane exceed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>She now is moulded new, and made moſt kind,</l>
               <l>Kindneſſe for kindneſſe kindly ſhe repayes:</l>
               <l>In ſeeling ſyllables he ſhewes his mind,</l>
               <l>And ſhe in ſpeaking t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ches hers bewrayes,</l>
               <l>And now if he imbrace her tender waſt,</l>
               <l>About his necke her armes are kindly caſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Why how now <hi>Argentile,</hi> what is this he,</l>
               <l>Whom you did ſay you would not loue ere while:</l>
               <l>Yes this is <hi>Curan,</hi> but you are not ſhe</l>
               <l>That ſpake thoſe words, you are not <hi>Argentile,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>At leaſt that <hi>Argentile</hi> coy and vnkind,</l>
               <l>you are not now, for you haue chang'd your mind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nor ſhall ſhe be condemn'd for this mutation,</l>
               <l>Or held light and vnſtable for this change:</l>
               <l>No, rather this deſerues much commerdation,</l>
               <l>When ſhe growes kind, that late was coy and ſtrange,</l>
               <l>Maids are not blam'd for this inconſtancie,</l>
               <l>But that which vnto this is contrary.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:30"/>
               <l>As ſhe that makes much ſhew of much good-will,</l>
               <l>And call's her ſelfe anothers, not her owne,</l>
               <l>Vowes and proteſteth to be conſtant ſtill,</l>
               <l>Yet afterwards though ſhe iuſt cauſe haue none,</l>
               <l>She flyeth off, and moſt vnkind doth proue,</l>
               <l>Fie, that fayre maydes ſhould be ſo falſe in loue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Well, now (in part) are crowned <hi>Curan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> wiſhes,</l>
               <l>For Loues Feaſt-royall he begins to taſt,</l>
               <l>Where the firſt ſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ce being ſuch ſweet diſhes,</l>
               <l>Superlatinely ſweet muſt be the laſt.</l>
               <l>Which now hee's like to taſte, for who ſo wes kiſſes</l>
               <l>In ſoyle and ſeaſon fit, and harueſt miſſes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I (vnexperienced) cannot expreſſe</l>
               <l>How much they Ioy'd imbracing and imbrac't.</l>
               <l>But they of this perhaps can neerely geſſe.</l>
               <l>That haue as high in fortunes loue beene plac't:</l>
               <l>Yet are their ioyes not perfect, though begunne,</l>
               <l>Not at their height, but like the forenoones ſunne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Which till they be, they badly brooke delayes,</l>
               <l>And on that wiſhed day agree'd they are,</l>
               <l>The interpoſed time they count by dayes,</l>
               <l>Not yeares, nor months, for t'will not reach ſo farre,</l>
               <l>Soone were they wed, their ioyes the want ſupplide</l>
               <l>Of meet ſolemnitie that haſt denide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Heauen vpon earth ſeemes to his ſhare to fall,</l>
               <l>That doth enioy a fayre, kind, vertuous wife:</l>
               <l>He that hath one that fayles herein, in all,</l>
               <l>He ſeemes to be in hell euen in this life.</l>
               <l>Prince <hi>Curans</hi> hap doth match the beſt of theſe,</l>
               <l>So exquiſitly well his choyce doth pleaſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:31"/>
               <l>She is adorn'd, ſhe is indude likewiſe</l>
               <l>With the beſt gifts of body, and of mind:</l>
               <l>And (whence much comfort doth to him ariſe)</l>
               <l>Shee's ſober, chaſt, ſtill, tractable and kind:</l>
               <l>Not ſuch a one as women are is ſhe,</l>
               <l>But ſhe is ſuch a one as they ſhould be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Shee doth not (for ſhe knowes ſhe ſhould not doo't)</l>
               <l>Beare wilfull ſway as they that headſhip ſhare:</l>
               <l>So that oftimes the head is made the foot.</l>
               <l>But they that beare this, too baſe minded are.</l>
               <l>Shall men be made their humours ſlaues, when they</l>
               <l>Were made for men, and were inioyn'd t'obey.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A louely ſweet Companion hath he got,</l>
               <l>Which heauen in loue did vpon him beſtow,</l>
               <l>Now happineſſe is falue vnto his lot,</l>
               <l>If happineſſe a man may haue below.</l>
               <l>For tis a hap beings happineſſe with it,</l>
               <l>To happen on a ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yce in all things fit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He that would be ſo bleſt, and ſo reioyce,</l>
               <l>Muſt heed, and good aduiſe (in chooſing) take,</l>
               <l>As well, or ill; a man doth make his choyce,</l>
               <l>Better, or worſe, his fortune he doth make.</l>
               <l>Nay, (which is more) the man that wiſely wiues,</l>
               <l>Much good to his poſterity deriues.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If ſhe be fayre, and of a comely ſeature,</l>
               <l>May not her like be then on her imprinted:</l>
               <l>And if ſhe be a kind good natur'd creature,</l>
               <l>Shee's not ſo to her ſelfe confin'd and ſtinted:</l>
               <l>But that the branch that ſprings from ſuch a tree,</l>
               <l>May beare like fruit, and of like nature be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:31"/>
               <l>If ſhee haue more then Nature can conuay,</l>
               <l>Good quallities by education got:</l>
               <l>They are communicable, and ſhe may</l>
               <l>Confer them on her Iſſue (may ſhe not?)</l>
               <l>Then he that makes good choyce deriues thereby</l>
               <l>Good to himſelfe and his poſteritie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If ſhe with goodnes be indu'de and grace,</l>
               <l>Why then (with her) doth ſhe Heauens bleſſing bring.</l>
               <l>And he within whoſe boſome theſe haue place,</l>
               <l>Will more make theſe his ayme then any thing.</l>
               <l>Theſe and what elſe may breede his bliſſe beſide,</l>
               <l>Are the Endowments of Prince <hi>Curans</hi> Bride.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And now though he till now had liu'd obſcure,</l>
               <l>Loſtin Loues Labrinth, doting ſo vpon her:</l>
               <l>Now that he hath her in poſſeſſion ſure,</l>
               <l>His vallour now redeems his morgadg'd honor.</l>
               <l>For Fiery quallitie from <hi>Mars</hi> hee tooke.</l>
               <l>Though ſhe could daunt him with an angrie looke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What could he doo, while he wore <hi>Beautyes</hi> Gyues?</l>
               <l>What could he do, while he <hi>Loues</hi> Priſoner was?</l>
               <l>He could not, did not then, but now he ſtriues,</l>
               <l>Euen <hi>Hercules</hi> in valour to ſurpaſſe.</l>
               <l>A brauer Knight, liu'd not in any Land,</l>
               <l>For Courage, Skill in Armes, and ſtrength of hand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Elſe-where he warr'd, and wonne, ere claim'd his right,</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Edell,</hi> in behalfe of <hi>Argentile:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(Deny'de of it) hee vowes in bloudy fight,</l>
               <l>To winne the ſame, if <hi>Fortune</hi> on him ſmile.</l>
               <l>If not, for what ſhall happe, prepar'de is hee,</l>
               <l>Braue mindes for Fortunes both, reſolued be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:32"/>
               <l>An Armie ſoone (though ſmall) he had prepar'd,</l>
               <l>(By him exampled) bold and guided well,</l>
               <l>And with the ſame on <hi>Edell</hi> falſe be war'd,</l>
               <l>Beneath his ſword on heapes his foe-men fell,</l>
               <l>Who (trembling) think hee's <hi>Mars</hi> himſelf, &amp; won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</l>
               <l>At his great ſtrokes, which kill like ſtroke of thunder.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He rides amongſt the thickeſt of his foes,</l>
               <l>And deales his almes about on euery ſide,</l>
               <l>So ſetting bloud abroach ſtill as he goes,</l>
               <l>That purple ſtreames along the field did glide,</l>
               <l>As oft as his vplifted ſword deſcends,</l>
               <l>So oft a ſoule he to Elizian ſends.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So many bodyes he depriu'd of breath,</l>
               <l>That weary waxed his victorious arme,</l>
               <l>While tugging <hi>Caron</hi> almoſt toyl'd to death,</l>
               <l>Tranſports the Ghoſts to'th' <hi>Stigion</hi> banks that ſwarm:</l>
               <l>And ſtill as faſt as <hi>Caron</hi> waftes them ore,</l>
               <l>Prince <hi>Curans</hi> conquering blade vnbodieth more.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To ward his blowes, their bucklers are too thinne,</l>
               <l>So are their armours to defend their fides,</l>
               <l>Not walls of yron ſecure their liues within,</l>
               <l>Through ſhield and ſhirt of male his Fauchion glides,</l>
               <l>Expelling from thoſe houſes fraile of clay,</l>
               <l>Thoſe fayre immortall gueſts that there did ſtay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So pearcing were the puſhes of his ſpeare,</l>
               <l>So ſharpe his thruſts, ſo ponderous his blowes,</l>
               <l>That his ſtrong foes though ten for one they were,</l>
               <l>Like to a ſtreame or ſtorme he ouerthrowes.</l>
               <l>For as a Lyon teares a tender Kid,</l>
               <l>So (vndermatcht) euen what he would he did.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:32"/>
               <l>There was no ſtrength that <hi>Curans</hi> ſtrength withſtood,</l>
               <l>He lops their armes, or elſe their heads he cleft,</l>
               <l>And ſo he paſſeth on imbru'd with bloud,</l>
               <l>The field behind all ſtrew'd with corps he left,</l>
               <l>A Gyant then ſuborn'd to <hi>Edels</hi> ayde,</l>
               <l>Oppoſ'd the Prince, his bloudy progreſſe ſtayde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Huge, ſterne this Gyant was, and paſſing proud,</l>
               <l>And ſcornd the Prince as much his vndermatch,</l>
               <l>And his baſe voyce he lifting vp aloud,</l>
               <l>Cries here he comes, that will thee ſoone diſpatch:</l>
               <l>But his proud brags could not Prince <hi>Curan</hi> ſeare,</l>
               <l>They rather to his courage wheſtones were.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Looke how thoſe vapors meet that out are blowne,</l>
               <l>From two huge Cannons, mouth to mouth oppoſ'd,</l>
               <l>The meeting of theſe Warriors ſuch was knowne,</l>
               <l>Such their incounter was, and ſo they cloſ'd,</l>
               <l>Long (to confound the Prince) the Gyant ſtriues,</l>
               <l>But failes, for <hi>Curan</hi> him of life depriues.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>(He dead) the reſt betakes themſelues to flight,</l>
               <l>And time it is for he that ſtayes he dyes:</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>Edell</hi> diſcontinued not the fight,</l>
               <l>So loath was he to looſe his dignities.</l>
               <l>Nor would he ceaſe till him Prince <hi>Curan</hi> ſlue,</l>
               <l>And payde the debt that long before was due.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Mercy was offered, he did it deſpiſe,</l>
               <l>And at the Prince with eager ſury ſmit,</l>
               <l>Iuſt angers flames ſhin'd then in <hi>Curans</hi> eyes:</l>
               <l>To ſurie, ruth, mercy to rage ſubmit.</l>
               <l>With that he ſtrikes, nor need he ſtrike againe,</l>
               <l>That ſtroke gaue end to <hi>Edels</hi> life and raigne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11927:33"/>
               <l>This done, vpon the Crowne Prince <hi>Curan</hi> ſeaſ'd,</l>
               <l>A pleaſing purchaſe though with perill bought,</l>
               <l>Nor durſt the people ſhew themſelues but pleaſ'd,</l>
               <l>They him applaud, and preſents to him brought,</l>
               <l>The Nobles too, preſent their loues cachone,</l>
               <l>And by thoſe ſteps, he mounts the kingly throne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Curan</hi> and <hi>Argentile</hi> now crowned are,</l>
               <l>She fayre, wiſe, vertuous, thence her prayſes roſe,</l>
               <l>He graue and iuſt, a thunderbolt in war,</l>
               <l>A Lambe, a Lyon, to his friendes and foes,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Northumber's</hi> crowne vndiuidable now,</l>
               <l>Euen till his death adorn'd his kingly brow.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Faults eſcaped.</head>
            <p>In the letter B. page 3. line 11, for beene fame, read being ſame. In C. pag. 5. line 3. for more powerfull, reade were powerfull. In C. pag. 7. line 12, for him runs, read it runs, In G. pag. 3. line 16. for our ſelues, reade our ſexe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:11927:33"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
